<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A philosophicall discourse concerning speech, conformable to the Cartesian principles Englished out of French.</title>
            <title>Discours physique de la parole. English</title>
            <author>Cordemoy, Géraud de, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12412516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12412516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 663:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A philosophicall discourse concerning speech, conformable to the Cartesian principles Englished out of French.</title>
                  <title>Discours physique de la parole. English</title>
                  <author>Cordemoy, Géraud de, d. 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 125, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Martin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy [London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Running title: A discourse of speech.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Discours physique de la parole.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Cordemoy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Language and languages.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Philoſophicall DISCOURSE Concerning SPEECH, Conformable to the <hi>CARTESIAN PRINCIPLES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated to The Moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed</hi> out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nted for <hi>John Martin,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Bell,</hi> a little without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe is the ſequel of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready appear'd in publick, under the Auguſt Name of Your MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY. I thought I was obliged to offer unto You the <hi>Firſt</hi> part of this Work, foraſmuch as having propoſ'd to my ſelf at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to give each man to conſider,
<pb facs="tcp:61559:3"/> 
               <hi>what He is,</hi> me thought, that Your MAJESTIE ſhould find in this conſideration more pleaſure than all other Men. I have the ſame reaſons to preſent this alſo to You, where I treat no more of the <hi>Knowledge of our ſelves,</hi> but of the <hi>Means to know oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>to be known by them.</hi> I ſhew, that this Means is SPEECH; I explain all the Effects thereof, and the better to diſcover the Cauſes, I carefully inquire into all, it borrows from the Body or the Soul. Theſe Cauſes, SIR, are ſo excellent in Your MAJESTIE, that You will doubtleſs have an incredible ſatisfaction to examine them: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things I am perſwaded, You will find more of it than any Man, when you ſhall conſider its <hi>Effects.</hi> You will ſee, it is <hi>Speech,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61559:3"/> which produceth what Your MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY loveth moſt, I mean, <hi>Glory,</hi> and you'll acknowledge, that to it you owe that Luſtre, which maketh Your MAJESTY out-ſhine all the Powers of the Earth. 'Tis by it, SIR, that You expreſs thoſe Generous Thoughts, which all tend to our Felicity; and 'tis by the ſame, that you have atchieved thoſe great things, which make all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſay, that <hi>You</hi> are the Greateſt Prince that ever was.</p>
            <p>I know, SIR, that men admire no leſs in Your MAJESTY the Faculty you have to be ſilent, than the Facility to ſpeak: I know, I ſay, that the Prudence you have to be ſilent, is one of the reaſons, which make others ſpeak ſo much of <hi>You.</hi> But I remember very
<pb facs="tcp:61559:4"/> well, that <hi>Secrecy,</hi> how favorable ſoever it is to great Deſſeins, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alone make them ſucceed, and that, how-ever Your MAJESTY hath advantagiouſly uſed it in all the Contrivances you have made for our Happineſs, you would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have obtain'd the Execution thereof, if you had not employ'd <hi>Speech;</hi> it was neceſſary, Orders ſhould be given for that. Indeed, SIR, you know how to give them as becoms a Prince, who needs none but himſelf to <hi>contrive</hi> and to <hi>reſolve.</hi> You alone know, why you give them, and thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, often not know the excellent End, Your MAJESTY propoſeth to your Self, but at the moment, which makes them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull.</p>
            <p>How amiable is <hi>Glory,</hi> when a
<pb facs="tcp:61559:4"/> Man thus owes it entirely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf! And how pure &amp; ſincere doth that of Your MAJESTY appear to me? Others, who have only <hi>Power</hi> for their Portion, heer themſelves praiſed for a thouſand Events, wherein their Conduct had no part: Words are alwayes found for them. But all the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Your MAJESTY, are ſo much above what can be ſaid of them, that thoſe to whom Praiſe coſts leaſt, complain they can find none to expreſſe them. Such an one hath demanded Ten <hi>years</hi> to write, what we have ſeen <hi>You</hi> do in Ten <hi>dayes:</hi> And another that knows, it requires leſs pains to compare <hi>Hero</hi>'s with one another, than to write their Praiſe, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to find like ones to Your MAJESTY, but could meet with
<pb facs="tcp:61559:5"/> none among all thoſe, whom An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity hath left recorded. Indeed, SIR, none of them are known, whoſe Paſſions have not guided all their Enterpriſes: the world hath ſeen him, whom paſt Ages have moſt boaſted of, to follow nothing but the motions of his Ambition, and, without at all conſidering the tranquillity of his Subjects, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the trouble into whole <hi>Aſia;</hi> whereas, SIR, all <hi>Europe</hi> hath ſeen You, young and victorious, ſhewing favour to your Enemies, that you might give Peace to your people: And it ſeeth at this very time, that <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets not a great Country expoſed to your Conqueſts, but deſires only what of right you can pretend to. This moderation, SIR, is the greateſt Virtue of <hi>Kings,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:61559:5"/> is it admirable in a Prince <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant</hi> enough to ſurpriſe the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in a ſeaſon, when the moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Spirits for war, do quit that painful exerciſe; and <hi>brave</hi> enough to execute himſelf, what the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt durſt not adviſe. What Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, SIR, could have ſtopt <hi>Your Majeſty,</hi> accompliſht with theſe Excellencies, if the Right of <hi>Bien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeance</hi> could have tempted you? But your Neighbours were to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelves afreſh, 'tis not Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition that hath armed you; 'tis from the hands of Juſtice, you hold that ſword, which ſubjects the <hi>Provinces</hi> in leſs time, than needs to march through them, <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Henaut</hi> may give te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony hereof to the reſt of the World. <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath made them know your Right, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:61559:6"/> you let them feel the force of your Armes; and 'tis known, that their Revolt is the only cauſe of thoſe great Exploits, which Hiſtory will never be able ſufficiently to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, and for which <hi>Poeſie</hi> it ſelf, which boaſts to ſpeak like the Gods, confeſſes to want expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But <hi>Sir,</hi> though <hi>Poeſy</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs the ſurpriſing effects of your Courage, take it in good part, that <hi>Philoſophy</hi> does rebuke the <hi>Exceſs</hi> of it, and that with her uſual liberty ſhe reproaches you for having expoſ'd your <hi>Sacred Perſon</hi> like that of a Common Souldier. This reproach would make up the Glory of every other Prince; but <hi>Sir,</hi> how could any man have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ'd <hi>You</hi> to poſterity, if that Great Heart, which is not given you but to ſuſtain the Deſtiny of
<pb facs="tcp:61559:6"/> 
               <hi>France,</hi> had made you be caſt away in this occaſion? One cannot praiſe enough this ardor, which maketh you quit pleaſures in the midſt of Winter; but how noble ſoever it be, it is to be blamed, when it makes you ſeek dangers, and when it expoſeth, againſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious</hi> Subjects, a life ſo precious to ſo many other faithful ones. Be pleaſed, <hi>Sir,</hi> to hearken to that zeal, which ſpeaks to you; It hath alwayes lov'd Kings, it hath never flatter'd them, and as it knows none greater than <hi>Your Self,</hi> it cannot at that time, when it intends to diſcourſe of <hi>SPEECH,</hi> make better uſe of it for the good of the Univerſe, than to tell what you owe to your own <hi>Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall add, <hi>Sir,</hi> that the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:61559:7"/> being to declare it ſelf upon this Subject by the mouth of a <hi>Man,</hi> it could not chooſe any one, whoſe Zeal were equal to mine. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Of Your Majeſty The moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt faithful Servant and Subject,</hi> CORDEMOY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:7"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Propoſed in the <hi>Six Diſcourſes,</hi> which preceded this,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Publiſht</hi> A. <hi>1666. under the Title,</hi> Le diſcernement du Corps &amp; de l' Ame; <hi>of which ſee</hi> Phil. Tranſ. No. <hi>17.</hi> p. <hi>306.</hi>
               </note> the means to know <hi>Our ſelves,</hi> &amp; made it manifeſt, that it only conſiſted in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning in us the Operations of the Soul, and thoſe of the Body. Now I propoſe the means of knowing <hi>Others,</hi> and that is <hi>SPEECH.</hi> I explain as far as I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>What it is;</hi> and pourſuant to my firſt deſſein, I endeavour in this Diſcourſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to diſtinguiſh what it borrows of the Soul, from what it holds of the Body.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To begin this Inquiry with the more certainty, I do not reaſon but upon what I have found <hi>within my ſelf</hi> in the <hi>Sixth Diſcourſe</hi> of the lately mentioned Book; and as if I had never yet been aſſured, there
<pb facs="tcp:61559:8"/> were other Men beſides my ſelf, I stay in the very beginning upon this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz. Whether it be neceſſary, that all the Bodies, which I ſee to be like mine, be united to Souls like mine?</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving with my ſelf not to believe it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I have ſuch evident ſignes thereof, that I may doubt no more of it. I examine, What thoſe Bodies do that's moſt ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and as long as I can rationally impute the Cauſe thereof to the <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of their <hi>Organs,</hi> I think, I may ſafely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, they have no Soul. But after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found in the ſole <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>parts</hi> of thoſe Bodies, that thence I can render a reaſon of Noiſe, the Sounds, the difference of the Voices, and the very Words utter'd by <hi>Echo's</hi> and Parrets, I am at length obliged to admit Souls in all the Bodies that reſemble mine, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it not poſſible for them to ſpeak to ſuch purpoſe, as they do, without being endowed with <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Next, having found, That to <hi>ſpeak</hi> is in general nothing elſe, but to <hi>Give ſignes of our Thoughts,</hi> I obſerve ſome of thoſe ſignes. The firſt, I conſider, are
<pb facs="tcp:61559:8"/> the Motions of the Eyes or Face, and ſuch Cryes, as ordinarily accompany the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtates of the Body: And I take notice, that they are naturally conjoyn'd with the Paſſions, of which the Soul is ſenſible on the occaſion of changes in the Body; and that the beſt way we have to manifeſt what ſhe ſuffers, is, not to ſtrain the Face, Eyes or Voice. I note likewiſe, that this way of explicating our ſelves, is the <hi>firſt</hi> of Tongues, and the <hi>moſt Univerſal,</hi> there being no Nation but underſtands it: But I obſerve at the ſame time, that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of Men hath made <hi>that</hi> the moſt deceitful of all. Beſides thoſe <hi>Natural</hi> ſignes of the Paſsions of the Soul, I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver others, which are but <hi>Inſtituted</hi> ones, by which ſhe can <hi>expreſs</hi> what ever ſhe <hi>conceives.</hi> I ſhew briefly the agreement and the difference of ſome of thoſe ſignes, to make all to be underſtood, what I intend to deduce from thence in this place; and reſerving to my ſelf to diſcourſe of it more ſtrictly, and more to my purpoſe thereafter, I ſtay to conſider, How one may invent a Language; How a man may learn the Tongue of a Country, where no body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands
<pb facs="tcp:61559:9"/> his; and laſtly, How Children learn to ſpeak. I admire, how their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is put to it in that Infant-age, to make them diſcern and diſtinguiſh the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every word; above all, the Order, which they follow for that purpoſe, appears to Me ſurpriſing, foraſmuch as 'tis alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether like that of the Grammar; ſo that ſeeing, how much this Art imitates Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I find no difficulty to make it out, How thoſe, that have given us the Rules thereof, have learnt them from little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And in this whole reſearch I meet with ſo many Arguments to evince the Diſtinction of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy and Soul, that to me it ſeems not, there can any thing be more evidently known, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> After ſome reflex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> important a Truth, I betake my ſelf, for the yet bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowing of the nature of <hi>Spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> to unfold in this place all what is to be found in it on the ſcore of the Body. I conſider therefore in him that ſpeaketh, the manner how the Air enters into the Lungs; why it maketh a ſound in iſſuing out at the Wind-pipe? How the Muſcles, that ſerve to open or ſhut this conduit, diverſifie the
<pb facs="tcp:61559:9"/> ſound? What parts of the mouth are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to determine it in a Voyce? What is the configuration of every one in theſe different terminations? and what is the Change of the Throat, the Tongue, the Teeth, and the Lips, in all the Articula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Which giveth me to underſtand, as much as needs, what <hi>Speech</hi> is, as far as it depends upon the Body. I obſerve with the ſame accurateneſs the effect, which by ſound is produced in the Ear and Brain of him, that heareth. I find, it is from the correſpondency between the <hi>Brain</hi> and the other parts of every Animal, that it can be ſo differently moved by different ſounds; and examining chiefly the uſe of the <hi>Nerves,</hi> which diffuſe themſelves from the Ear to all the parts ſerving to form the voice, I diſcover the reaſons of many odd effects, and amongst them, of certain Birds imitating the ſinging of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the ſound of our Muſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and often our very Words.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> I alſo draw from thence a convincing argument, that <hi>Brutes</hi> need no ſoul to cry, or to be moved by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyces, or even to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſound of our words; and that if
<pb facs="tcp:61559:10"/> the cry of thoſe, that are of the ſame <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> diſpoſeth them to approach one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and maketh thoſe that are of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent kind, to retire; the cauſe of <hi>that</hi> is to be ſought no where elſe but in their Bodies and the different conſtruction of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. But at the ſame time I find, that in Men, the motion of the parts, which ſerve for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce, or of thoſe that are moved by it, is ever accompanied with ſome <hi>thoughts;</hi> and that in <hi>Speech</hi> there are alwayes two things, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Voyce,</hi> which cannot proceed but from the <hi>Body;</hi> and the <hi>Signification</hi> or the <hi>Idea,</hi> that is joyn'd therewith, which cannot come but from the <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> And becauſe hitherto I have ſaid almoſt nothing of the <hi>Voice,</hi> of <hi>Writing,</hi> and of <hi>Signes,</hi> but what may ſerve to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what thoſe three wayes of expreſsing our thoughts have common (there having been no occaſion, ſooner to obſerve the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of each) I take notice in this place of <hi>three</hi> ſorts of <hi>Signes,</hi> of <hi>two</hi> ſorts of <hi>Writing,</hi> and of <hi>two</hi> of <hi>Voices.</hi> I ſtay principally upon the laſt, on which occaſion I finiſh the explication of what the order
<pb facs="tcp:61559:10"/> of the precedent matters had not permitted me to explicate ſooner, touching the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or difficulty, there is in joyning certain <hi>Idea's</hi> to certain <hi>Words,</hi> when we learn a Language: And making out as accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I can, how all that is done, I find, that the trouble which ſome have to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> or to <hi>explain</hi> themſelves, is not an imperfection in the Soul; and that that marvellous facility, which others enjoy to expreſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mſelves, proceeds only from an happy Diſpoſition of the Brain, and of all the parts that ſerve for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce or for the Motions of the Body.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> On which occaſion I inquire into the natural cauſes of <hi>Eloquence,</hi> and find, that to the perfection thereof are required two talents at once, which by birth are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver given to one and the ſame perſon, but yet that one of them being furniſht by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the defects of the other may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd by <hi>Art.</hi> And having remarked, that that is not reciprocal, I declare (as far as I may in a Diſcourſe where I am to explain but the <hi>Principles</hi>) whence thoſe defects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and by what they may be corrected; and I do even examine, without ſtepping
<pb facs="tcp:61559:11"/> into the <hi>Ethicks,</hi> why an <hi>Orator</hi> ought to be a <hi>good</hi> man, and how much <hi>Lying</hi> may impair the force or the grace of his action.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Laſtly, having conſidered ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how much <hi>Eloquence</hi> depends from the Temperament, and how it may be corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or perfected by exerciſe, I examine, Whether it is to be met with among <hi>Spirits</hi> not united to Bodies: Which obliges me to enquire into the manner, after which they may manifeſt their thoughts to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and it makes me diſcover, that even <hi>our</hi> Spirits would enjoy a more eaſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication among themſelves, if the ſtrict <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion they have with the Body, did not indiſpenſably oblige them to make uſe of <hi>Signes.</hi> The ſame raciocination teaches me alſo, that the difficulty we meet with in entertainments, is not to conceive the <hi>thoughts</hi> of thoſe, that ſpeak to us, but to unwrap it from the <hi>Signes</hi> they uſe to expreſs it in, which often do not ſute with it: Whence I conclude, that the Thought of one Spirit is alwayes clear to another from the very inſtant he can perceive it. And this truth (which I diſcuſs as far as
<pb facs="tcp:61559:11"/> I am capable) ſerves me to reſolve thoſe difficulties, which others have thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurmountable but by ſubmiſſion to <hi>Faith.</hi> I well know, 'tis <hi>Faith,</hi> that muſt teach us, whether ſundry things have a <hi>being</hi> indeed; but there is not alwayes need of its aid to <hi>conceive</hi> them. It belongs to it, for example, to tell us, whether there be other Spirits more enlightned, that ſerve to direct ours; but when once it hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to us that truth, me thinks, our <hi>reaſon</hi> can attain to it. And I eſteem, that reflecting a little on what the thred of my ſubject hath obliged me to write of it in this Tract, we ſhall find it more eaſie to conceive, how pure Spirits can inſpire us with their ſentiments, than to conceive, how one <hi>Man</hi> can inſpire his thoughts to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>I might have proceeded further in this Inquiry, but having propoſed to my ſelf only to examine what ſerves to <hi>Speech,</hi> I thought I was to make an end, after I had conſider'd the ſundry wayes by which <hi>Thoughts</hi> may be communicated, ſeeing that that is properly, what we call <hi>To ſpeak.</hi> I could wiſh, that the diſcourſe I
<pb facs="tcp:61559:12"/> have made of it, might prove as pleaſant to others as the reflexions, it hath obliged me to make, have been to me. I avow, they have been all the divertiſement I have enjoyed during the laſt Vacations; and as it is, at leaſt in that time, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to comply with our inclinations, the pleaſure I have found in it, ſollicits me ſtrongly to ſpend in the ſame manner all the other hours, wherein I may be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to divert my ſelf. To conclude, this Argument is ſo pleaſant and ſo fertile, that one needs but to propoſe it, and it will beget a thouſand pleaſing thoughts: And I doubt not, but all thoſe that excell me in <hi>genius,</hi> will find by occaſion of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe a thouſand pretty things, which I have omitted; ſo that without boaſting of my Book, I may affirm, that the more wit a man hath, the more pleaſure he will find to read it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61559:12"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF SPEECH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the Bodies, I ſee in the World, I perceive ſome, that are in all things like mine, and I confeſs, I have a great inclination to believe, that they are united to Souls, as mine is. But when I come to conſider, that my Body hath ſo many operations diſtinct from thoſe of my Soul, and that nothing of what maketh it ſubſiſt depends at all from Her, I think I have at leaſt ground
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61559:13"/> to doubt, that thoſe Bodies are united to Souls, until I have examin'd all their actions: And I do even ſee, that by the maximes of good ſenſe I ſhall be obliged to believe, that they have no Soul, if they do only ſuch things, whereof I have found in my ſelf that the Body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may be the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Thus if I ſee; that the Objects make different impreſſions on them by the Eyes, Ears, Noſe or Touch, and if I ſee them eat, ſleep, wake, feed, breath, walk, and dye, nothing of all that ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to make me believe, that there is any other thing in them but a certain diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of organs and parts, which indeed is admirable, but yet ſo dependent from the courſe and order of the other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that I have acknowledged <hi>that</hi> to be the only cauſe in me of Nutrition Sleep, Reſpiration, and of the power which objects have to move the Brain ſo many ſurpriſing wayes.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, I have obſerv'd, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in Thoughts alwayes accompani'd in me moſt of the motions of my Organs; but yet 'tis true alſo, that by the exacteſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61559:13"/> preciſeneſs, with which I have diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh't what was in all my operations on the account of the Body, and what on the ſcore of the Soul, I have found manifeſtly, that if I had nothing but the Body, I might have all what appears to me in the other Bodies, which reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mine.</p>
            <p>It behoves me therefore to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thoſe Bodies neerer, and to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether I may not perceive by any of their Actions, that they are ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Souls. I ſee, that ordinarily they are carried to places, where the Air ſeems moſt proper to entertain by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration a due temper in the Bloud. I ſee, that they withdraw likewiſe from places, where the Cold might too much retard the motion, and from thoſe, where the Heat might render it too quick. I ſee, that they often flye with vehemence from the encounter of many other Bodies, that appear to me of a Shape and Motion capable to deſtroy them; and I ſee alſo, that they approach thoſe, which may be beneficial to them: And all theſe actions appear to me to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61559:14"/> be done with a diſcerning ſuch as I find in me, when I do the ſame actions.</p>
            <p>Mean time, when I reflect, that I have found by other Contemplations, that the ſole <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Organs</hi> is the cauſe of all thoſe operations in me, I fear I affirm too much, if I attribute the different motions of the Bodies, that ſurround me, to another cauſe, than to the agreement, there is between their Brain and the Objects; and then, as long as I do not ſee them do but what is for their good, as to eat, to drink, to ſeek after coolneſs or warmth, and whatever may maintain them in a ſtate ſutable to their nature, I am not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, there is any other thing in them but the <hi>Organs,</hi> which may ſuffice for that.</p>
            <p>But me-thinks, I ſee them often do things that relate not at all to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor their preſervation: I ſee ſome of them that meet with other Bodies, the encounter whereof muſt in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance deſtroy them: I ſee even ſome of them quit the food they need, and the places that ſhelter them from what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61559:14"/> may be noxious to them, to run thither, where their deſtruction is in a manner certain: And that makes me reaſonably preſume, that in ſuch occaſions they may be guided by ſomewhat, that is very differing from themſelves. For when I ſee, that they approch reſolutely to what is deſtructive to them, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon what may preſerve them, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſcribe thoſe effects to this Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal proportion or agreement, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and the Objects: And ſince I have often noted, that notwithſtanding the bent my body hath towards certain things, and that in ſpight of the force, wherewith its ſtructure makes it avoid others, I have yet a will <hi>contrary</hi> to its natural diſpoſition, which makes it often to be tranſported after a manner quite differing from that, it would be, if it follow'd nothing elſe but the diſpoſition of its organs, and the force which the objects exerciſe upon it; I can hardly keep my ſelf from believing, but that the motion of all the Bodies, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble mine, depends from a will like mine.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61559:15"/>
            <p>In a word, I can ſcarce doubt of it, when I reflect on the chain of many of their actions, that have no relation at all to what can preſerve them; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, the connexion, I find between the <hi>Words,</hi> I hear them utter at all times, ſeems to demonſtrate to me, that they have <hi>Thoughts.</hi> For although I do very well conceive, that a meer Engin might utter ſome words, yet I underſtand at the ſame time, that if the organs, which ſhould diſtribute the wind, or open the pipes, whence thoſe voices ſhould iſſue, had a certain ſettled order among them, they could never change it, ſo that when the firſt Voice were heard, thoſe that were wont to follow it, would needs be heard alſo, provided the wind were not wanting to the Engin; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the words, which I hear utter'd by Bodies, made like mine, have almoſt never the ſame ſequel. On the other hand I obſerve, that thoſe Words are the ſame, which I would uſe to expreſs my thoughts by to other ſubjects, that ſhould be capable to conceive them. Laſtly, the more I obſerve the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61559:15"/> effect, which my words produce, when I utter them before thoſe Bodies, the more methinks that they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: and thoſe, which they utter, anſwer ſo perfectly to the ſenſe of mine, that there appears not any more ground to doubt, but that a ſoul per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms that in them, which mine doth in me</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, in purſuance to that firme reſolution, I have taken to admit nothing in my belief, but what ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear evident to me; after I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered it enough, not to need to fear, I deceive my ſelf; I will more ſeriouſly than ever reflect upon all what ſerves for <hi>Speech,</hi> ſince that is the ſureſt way, I have, to know, whether all the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which ſo perfectly reſemble mine, are indeed Men as I am.</p>
            <p>The firſt, which ſeems to me worthy conſideration, is, that there are many Bodies, that can cauſe a noiſe by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the Air, and that that noiſe may be different, according to the different concourſe of Bodies, or the diverſity of their parts: In which regard 'tis ſo far,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61559:16"/> there ſhould be need of ſuppoſing Souls in Bodies to produce that effect, that on the contrary I know, that the Noiſe not happening but becauſe the Air is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, the cauſe of it cannot rationally be imputed but to what is capable to impel it, that is, to a Body.</p>
            <p>I know alſo, that by the aid of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks</hi> one may ſo fitly adjuſt certain Bodies to one another, that they ſhall be able to compoſe inſtruments capable to make agreeable ſounds, and even to imitate the Songs, which I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſed to expreſs grief or joy.</p>
            <p>I know further, that Rocks and other like Bodies can make us underſtand not only Sounds, as Muſical Inſtruments do, but alſo Words perfectly articulated. 'Tis true, I know, that they form them not, and that, as they would repel a ball to him that ſhould caſt it on them, they do no more but ſend back the words to him that hath utter'd them, that is, they drive back to him the ſame air that was driven to them, without changing any thing in that impreſſion; which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it carry the words ſo far from the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61559:16"/> places, where they are pronounced, when there is nothing to ſtop them.</p>
            <p>I conceive likewiſe, as I have already ſaid, that <hi>Art</hi> may go ſo far as to frame an Engin, that ſhall articulate words like thoſe, which I pronounce; but then I conceive at the ſame time, that it would only pronounce thoſe, that were deſign'd it ſhould pronounce, and that it would always pronounce them in the ſame order.</p>
            <p>So that I ought not haſtily to believe, that whatſoever can make a Noiſe, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſound, form voices, or pronounce words, hath <hi>Thoughts;</hi> and I ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, to take notice, that the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Workman, to whom I owe the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of my Body, hath ſo mechanical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed and order'd all the parts, and principally thoſe that ſerve for the voice, that to form <hi>it</hi> I need no Soul: The ſole motions of the Muſcles, the Breaſt and the Diaphragme can make the Air enter into my Lungs, or let it out; and the only ſcituation of the Cartilages of the <hi>Larynx,</hi> diverſly changed by the ſmall Muſcles which ſerve to move
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61559:17"/> them, may be the cauſe of a thouſand ſharp or grave founds, ſweet or ſhrill, piercing or weak, according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent flexures, the air receives in that paſſage.</p>
            <p>I ought alſo to conſider, that when I articulate divers words, it is only becauſe that the Air, which is already let out of the throat, is diverſly agitated, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Muſcles of my Tongue move the ſame either upwards or downwards in my mouth; or elſe becauſe being near to get out, it is agitated according to the different ways, in which my Teeth or my Lips can apply themſelves to one another by the motion of <hi>their</hi> Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>Beſides I muſt conſider, that the Muſcles, which, ſerve to move all thoſe parts, are not moved themſelves, but according as my <hi>Brain</hi> is agitated, and that that can be ſo, a thouſand different ways by the <hi>Organs</hi> of <hi>Hearing;</hi> my ſoul having no other part in all thoſe motions, but to perceive the effects thereof.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I am to take notice, that there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61559:17"/> is ſo great a communication and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency between the Nerves of the Ear, and thoſe of the <hi>Larynx,</hi> that whenſoever any ſound agitates the Brain, there flow immediately ſpirits towards the Muſcles of the <hi>Larynx,</hi> which duely diſpoſe them to form a ſound altogether like that, which was juſt now ſtriking the Brain. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I well conceive, that there needs ſome <hi>time</hi> to facilitate thoſe motions of the Muſcles of the Throat, ſo that the Sounds, which excite the Brain the firſt time, cannot be eaſily expreſſed by the Throat, yet notwithſtanding I doe as well conceive, that by virtue of repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them it will come to paſs, that the Brain, which thereby is often ſhaken in the ſame places, ſends ſuch a plenty of ſpirits through the nerves, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in the Muſcles of the Throat, that at length they eaſily move <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, which ſerve for that action, as tis requiſite they ſhould be moved to form Sounds like thoſe, that have ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Brain.</p>
            <p>Thus it is not enough, that Bodies
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61559:18"/> make Sounds, form Voices, and even articulate Words like thoſe, by which I expreſs what I think, to perſwade me, that they <hi>think</hi> what-ever they ſeem to <hi>ſay.</hi> For example, I ought not be ſo raſh as to believe, that a <hi>Parret</hi> hath any <hi>thought,</hi> when he pronounces ſome <hi>Words:</hi> For beſides that I have obſerved, that after having repeated to him exceedingly often the ſame words in a certain order, he never returneth but the ſelf ſame words, and in the ſame coherence; It ſeems to me, that ſince he does not make theſe returns to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he imitates men leſs, than Echo's doe, which never anſwer but what hath been ſaid to them; and if there be any difference between Parrets and Echo's, it is, that <hi>Rocks,</hi> toſſing back the Air without changing at all the impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it hath received, render the ſame voices, that have ſtruck them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Parrets</hi> form another voice like that, which hath ſtruck the ear, and often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat words, which are ſaid to them no more. But in ſhort, as I cannot ſay, that Rocks ſpeak, when they return
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61559:18"/> words, ſo I dare not affirm, that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets ſpeak, when they repeat them. For it ſeems to me, that to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> is not to repeat the ſame words, which have ſtruck the ear, but to utter others to their purpoſe and ſutable to them. And as I have reaſon to believe that none of the Bodies, that make <hi>Echo's,</hi> do <hi>think</hi> though I hear them repeat my words, ſeing they never render them but in the order, I utter'd them in; I ſhould by the ſame reaſon judge, that <hi>Parrets</hi> do not think neither.</p>
            <p>But not to examine any further, how it is with Parrets, and ſo many other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whoſe figure is very different from mine, I ſhall continue the Inquiry, which I need, to know the <hi>inward</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of thoſe, who reſemble me ſo perfectly <hi>without;</hi> and for that purpoſe I think, I may, after the diſquiſition I have been making of all what cauſeth noiſe, ſounds, voices, and words, eſtabliſh for a Principle,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if the Bodies, which are like mine, had nothing but the facilneſs of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Words, I ſhould not therefore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61559:19"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they had the advantage of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united to Souls: But then, if I finde by all the Experiments, I am capable to make, that they uſe ſpeech as I do, I ſhall think, I have infallible reaſon to beleive that they have a ſoul as I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make this examen in ſuch an order, as leaves me no ſuſpicion at all to have deceived my ſelf, I muſt conſider before all, what I mean by SPEECH. To <hi>ſpeak</hi> (in my opinion) is nothing elſe, but to make known what we think to that creature which is capable to underſtand it. And ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the Bodies, which reſemble mine, have Souls, I ſee, that the only means to expreſs to one another what we think, is, to give to our ſelves exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſignes thereof.</p>
            <p>But, me thinks, I have found, that there are many ſignes common to them and me, by which we underſtand one another: for ſeing that they anſwer to my ſignes by other ſignes, which give me images agreeable to what I think, I do not believe I am deceived, when I perſwade my ſelf, that they have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61559:19"/> my thought, and that the new thought, which their ſignes have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in me, is really that, which they have.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I ſee, I can agree with ſome of them, that what commonly ſignifies one thing, ſhall ſignifie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and that this ſucceeds ſo, as that there are none but thoſe, with whom I have agreed about it, that appear to me to underſtand what I think.</p>
            <p>Whence I conceive; that thoſe <hi>ſigns</hi> are of <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> and as that <hi>Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> neceſſarily ſuppoſeth reaſon and thoughts in thoſe, that are capable to agree about it, I ſhould, it may be, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance nothing raſhly, if I <hi>now</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that thoſe Bodies are united to Souls.</p>
            <p>But that, which might trouble me here, is, that if there be <hi>ſigns</hi> of <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> I think, I know others, that are alltogether <hi>natural.</hi> For example, all thoſe, by which I expreſs my paſſions without any deſign to do ſo: Thus a ſmiling Meen, and certain motions of my eies, or of the other parts of my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61559:20"/> Face, make me often conſider, when I conſult with the Looking-glaſs, that if others ſaw me, they would know my ſadneſs, my joy, or the other paſſions ſtirring in me: And that, it may be (If thoſe bodies reſembling mine, have Souls) is the ſureſt means to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to them the different conſtitutions of my Soul.</p>
            <p>Yet, if I take good heed, I can ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe ſigns very deceitful. For I find, that though naturally I appear outwardly chearful or ſad, when I am ſo indeed, yet I have the power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the motions of my face and eyes, ſo as to make them have an Air quite differing from that, which they would have, if I left their motions free: Which gives me to underſtand, that though naturally certain motions of my face, and even of my whole Body have been joyn'd to ſome of my <hi>thoughts,</hi> yet this conjunction is not ſo neceſſary, but that I can ſometimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, by joyning thoſe thoughts to other motions. And though indeed, that give me much pain, yet I conceive,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61559:20"/> that as we may form an eaſy habit of what at firſt appears very difficult, I could alſo render theſe changes eaſy enough to me.</p>
            <p>But, what I am moſt of all to obſerve here is, that, although it be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, that, as long as my Soul is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my Body, (for the conſervation whereof ſhe hath divers paſſions) her joy, her ſadneſs, her deſires, or her fear be alwayes joyn'd with the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the good or ill diſpoſition of that Body can beget in the Brain; as alſo that that correſpondence which is between the parts of the Brain and thoſe of the Face or Eyes, and all ſuch as are external, be the cauſe, that what is <hi>within,</hi> may never change, unleſs there be marks of it <hi>without;</hi> yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſince thoſe exteriour marks have no neceſſary relation but to the changes of the Brain, and that the ſole condition of the Body may be the cauſe thereof, it might happen, that though the Bodies, which reſemble mine, ſhould not be united to Souls, that yet they would have the ſame motions of eyes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61559:21"/> and face, which I often perceive in me, according as they ſhould be well or ill diſpos'd within; ſo that thoſe external ſignes, ſo like in thoſe Bodies and mine, are not alone an infallible argument, that thoſe bodies are endow'd with Souls.</p>
            <p>Further, ſince thoſe motions of the face and eyes, and even thoſe cryes, that are never wanting, when nothing conſtrains them, to follow the different conditions of the Body by reaſon of the relation, there is between all the parts thereof, may very properly be call'd the <hi>natural ſignes</hi> of the State, the Body is in; I ſhall be careful to forbear, when the eyes and face, or even the Cryes of thoſe Bodies ſhall not appear to me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited but by the objects, that may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit or hurt them, to believe, that thoſe external motions are the ſigns of any <hi>Thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, when I ſhall ſee, that thoſe Bodies ſhall make ſignes, that ſhall have no reſpect at all to the ſtate they are in, nor to their conſervation: when I ſhall ſee, that thoſe ſigns ſhall agree
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61559:21"/> with thoſe which I ſhall have made to expreſs my <hi>thoughts:</hi> When I ſhall ſee, that they ſhall give me <hi>Idea's,</hi> I had not before, and which ſhall relate to the thing, I had already in my mind: Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when I ſhall ſee a great ſequel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their ſignes and mine, I ſhall not be reaſonable, If I believe not, that they are ſuch, as I am.</p>
            <p>Thus I have no more cauſe to doubt concerning this point; for I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a thouſand like tryals, and I have not onely ſeen a great connexion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their <hi>ſigns</hi> and my <hi>thoughts,</hi> but I have alſo found ſo great an one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>their</hi> ſignes and <hi>mine,</hi> that I can doubt no longer of their <hi>thoughts.</hi> And if the power, I have to hinder, that the exterior motions of my face, and the other ſignes of my paſſions may not expreſs them, hath been one of the reaſons, I have had to acknowledge, that my thoughts were very different from the motions, that are wont to accompany them; I can now aſſure, not onely that thoſe other Bodies, which reſemble mine, have <hi>thoughts,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61559:22"/> but alſo, though they can, as I my ſelf, not let them alwaies be <hi>ſo</hi> joyned to the motions, which uſe to ſignifie them, that one ought alwaies to truſt them; Yet I have found, that they knew the art of conſtraining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and frequently after many ſigns on their ſide, and mine, which ſhew'd me that they underſtood my thoughts, and made me believe that I underſtood theirs, I perceived, they had a deſign to deceive me.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſince I may doubt no longer, that the Bodies, which reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mine, are united to Souls, and in a word, ſince I am aſſured, that there are other men beſides my ſelf, I think I ought carefully to inquire into what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to know of <hi>Speech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I have diſcours'd of it but in <hi>general,</hi> and ſaid only, that <hi>To ſpeak</hi> was to give ſigns of one's Thought: But in regard that the little reflexion, I have made on theſe ſignes, hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſcover'd to me ſo important a truth, and that I alſo ſee, that thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61559:22"/> ſame ſignes are the only means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Society amongſt Men, which is the greateſt good, they have in this World, I intend as much as I can to obſerve the different ſorts of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their properties, and to endeavour to diſcover all the wonders of them, to learn all their uſes.</p>
            <p>One of the chief things, I finde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of conſideration touching theſe <hi>ſigns,</hi> is, That they have not any reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the <hi>Thoughts,</hi> which men joyn to them by <hi>inſtitution.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, whether we expreſs our thoughts by <hi>geſtures,</hi> by <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> or by <hi>chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,</hi> (which are the three ſorts of the moſt uſed <hi>ſigns,</hi> by which we manifeſt our <hi>thoughts</hi>) we cannot but ſee (if we conſider it with ſome attention) that there is nothing leſs reſembling our Thoughts, than is all that, which ſerves us to expreſs them. For, when a man, to declare that he agrees not with me in ſuch or ſuch a thing, is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his head, and when the better to expreſs it, he moveth his throat, tongue, teeth and lips, to form words,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61559:23"/> or takes paper and with a pen trace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> characters to write it to me, I ſee ſo little reſemblance betwixt all thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of the Head, of the Mouth, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Hand, and what they teach me that I cannot enough wonder how they <hi>ſo eaſily</hi> give me the underſtanding of a thing, they <hi>ſo ill</hi> repreſent.</p>
            <p>But what is moſt admirable herein is, That this vaſt difference between thoſe <hi>Signs</hi> and our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> doth by marking to us <hi>that,</hi> which is between our Body and Soul, teach us at the ſame time the whole Secret of their Union. At leaſt methinks, that that ſtrict uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the ſole Inſtitution or men is able to ſettle betwixt certain exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Motions, and our Thoughts, is to him that will conſider it, the beſt means to conceive, wherein in truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the Union of the Body and the Soul. For cartainly, if we do conceive, that men can by <hi>inſtitution</hi> joyn certain Motions to certain Thoughts, it cannot be hard to conceive, that the Author of Nature, in forming a Man, ſo well unites ſome Thoughts of his Soul to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61559:23"/> ſome motions of his Body, that thoſe motions cannot be raiſed in the Body, but the thoughts muſt alſo be forthwith excited in the Soul, and that recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally as ſoon as the Soul will have the Body move after a certain manner, it be ſo at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>For the reſt, 'tis evident, that from this ſo neceſſary relation, which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of Nature maintain betwixt the body and the ſoul, it is that that neceſſity of making Signs to expreſs our thoughts hath its riſe. For, ſeeing the Soul can have no <hi>though,</hi> but at the occaſion whereof there will be made a <hi>motion</hi> in the Body, and that alſo ſhe cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any <hi>Idea</hi> of what is <hi>without</hi> but by the motions excited <hi>in</hi> the Body, which ſhe animateth; it muſt needs be, that two Souls united to two different Bodies do expreſs their thoughts by <hi>Motions,</hi> or, if you will, by outward <hi>Signs.</hi> But to know perſectly, how that is done, there needs, in my opinion, to be made but a little reflexion on what I have already obſerv'd about the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal differences of Signs, on the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61559:24"/> cauſe of each, and on the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, men have to uſe them.</p>
            <p>And firſt, if it be true, that certain motions of the Face, and certain Cryes do naturally follow certain conditions of the Body by vertue of the relation, which is between all the parts thereof, we muſt believe, that the thoughts, which are naturally joyn'd to thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Face, and to theſe Cryes, are the paſſions, which the Soul ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers at the occaſion of the State, the Body is in; ſo that if a man hath well obſerved his Eyes, his Face, and all the outward parts of his Body du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time he hath been in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain paſſions, he hath been able, ſeeing the ſame motions in another man, to Judg, that that man felt the ſame paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: 'Tis true, if at times he hath been ſo dextrous as to conſtrain himſelf in the like ſtate, he may have learn'd to miſtruct thoſe ſignes; but ſtill 'tis manifeſt, that they are naturally proper to declare paſſions, and that the beſt means to make one underſtand what the Soul ſuffers, is, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61559:24"/> the Face, the Eyes or the Voice; 'tis the moſt natural way to expreſs our thoughts; 'tis alſo the firſt of all the Languages, and the moſt Univerſal that is in the World, ſince there is no Nation, but underſtands it.</p>
            <p>There are two other wayes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs not only the Paſſions of the Soul, but alſo what ever ſhe conceiveth, <hi>viz. Speech,</hi> and <hi>Writing;</hi> which, to ſpeak truth, are but one and the ſame thing. For, men having obſerv'd, that they could form different <hi>Voices</hi> or diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Letters,</hi> did agree, that the <hi>words</hi> or the <hi>Letters</hi> ſhould ſignify <hi>Things,</hi> and they expreſs'd themſelves by the one or by the other of thoſe wayes, according as it was more convenient to the State, they were in; if they were abſent, the <hi>letters</hi> which remain after they are drawn were more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for them, becauſe they could be carry'd where a <hi>voice</hi> could not; but if they were preſent, words utter'd ſeem'd to them a more facil way to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs themſelves; and laſtly, if there were ſome, that had not the freedom
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61559:25"/> of the voice, he might by Characters expoſe to the Eye the Signs of his Thought: So that if there be any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al difference 'twixt <hi>Writing</hi> and <hi>Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 'tis, that in <hi>Speaking</hi> we make uſe of the <hi>Voyce,</hi> and in <hi>Writing</hi> of <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,</hi> which 'tis true, are very differing ſigns, but in both we expreſs our ſelves by things external and corporeal, which by <hi>inſtitution</hi> are made to ſignify what we think; and that <hi>in general</hi> is what we call <hi>Speaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being ſo, there is no man, that may not conceive, that one can <hi>lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a Language, or a way of Writing, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that one may even <hi>invent</hi> them. For is evident, that whether we learn them or invent them, we do nothing elſe bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agree, that certain <hi>Characters</hi> ſhall ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie certain thoughts. It appears alſo that if there be a difference between learning and inventing them; it is, that in <hi>learning</hi> them, we onely furniſh our ſelves with the ſignes, already agreed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by other men, but in <hi>inventing</hi> them we are Maſters of the Inſtitution, which maketh that the <hi>Words</hi> or <hi>Characters</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61559:25"/> ſignifie rather one thing than another: And by this means it is, that almoſt all the Nations have made to themſelves different Languages.</p>
            <p>But as 'tis eaſie to conceive, how men that ſpeak one and the ſame Language, may agree amongſt themſelves about the means of inventing new ones; I ſhall ſtay a while to conſider, how a perſon that hath no knowledge at all of the Language of a Country, may learn it, though thoſe of that Country ſhould know nothing of his.</p>
            <p>For that end I conceive, that apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf at firſt to know the names of the things, moſt neceſſary for <hi>him,</hi> he ſhould attentively hearken to all that ſhould be ſaid by thoſe, who ſhould hold in their hands, or ſhew any of thoſe things; and the word they ſhould repeat oftneſt in ſpeaking of that thing, being moſt likely the name of it, he ſhould, when he pronounces that word, at the ſame time, to obtain the thing, uſe ſome ſign to manifeſt he had need of it; and if, making that ſhow, and and giving to underſtand his need, he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61559:26"/> ſhould not name it aright, men would not be wanting to tell him the right name of it; ſo that he might by the like informations in a ſhort time know the name of many things, and how little wit ſoever he had, obſerve, above all things, the words that ſhould be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him oftneſt, by anſwering to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers queſtions, he ſhould make of the name of the things, by pointing to them. For, in all appearance, the words, that ſhould be found in all the anſwers nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the name of every thing, would ſignifie, <hi>That is called,</hi> or <hi>named;</hi> ſo that he would have no more to do but to repeat <hi>them,</hi> for the making of new queſtions.</p>
            <p>When he ſhall have learnt by this means the names of many things, he might then, according as thoſe things ſhould be beneficial or hurtful, obſerve the words, which thoſe, who ſhould manifeſt they were affected with them, ſhould uſe to expreſs what they meant by them, and by this way learn the words, which ſignifying the <hi>qualities</hi> are alwayes added to thoſe, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61559:26"/> the things, to which thoſe qualities belong.</p>
            <p>Next, when he ſhall ſee done certain actions, <hi>e.g.</hi> of mounting, deſcending, going away, and coming, he might ask, <hi>How that was called,</hi> and when he ſhall know words enow to form diſcourſes, wherein he might mingle <hi>Verbs</hi> with <hi>Nouns,</hi> that is to ſay, what he thought concerning the things and their actions, he could then make himſelf to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, though he ſhould as yet ſpeak improperly as to the words and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>But to ſee, that that is not impoſſible, we need only to conſider, that ſuch a thing muſt often happen to Travellers: And ſhould not <hi>Men of age</hi> find means to make themſelves to be underſtood in a Country where they come, ſince <hi>little Children</hi> find them to learn the language of the Country where they are born? They bring nothing with them into the world, but what Nature gives to all men, to expreſs pain, joy, or other paſſions: Mean while, <hi>that</hi> ſuffices them; and how little time ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61559:27"/> they have lived, they ſo well ſtudy the looks of their Nurſe, that ſhe can make them weep or laugh, by only looking on them. Thus they eaſily know the paſſions of thoſe that come near them, by the external motions, which are the natural ſignes of them.</p>
            <p>They are ſomewhat longer to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>ſignes,</hi> that men have <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted</hi> to ſignifie <hi>things;</hi> but the need they have of ſome of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, renders them ſo attentive to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll what is ſaid of thoſe things, when they perceive that they are touched or ſhewn by the hand, that at length they learn the name of it. 'Tis true, that ordinarily we endeavour to excite in them ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion (as joy) by ſome cry, which accomp nying the ſhew that is made to them of the things at the ſame time, when we tell them their names, maketh th t they are more attentive to them, and by being more affected with them by this means, they retain them the better.</p>
            <p>But in the taking p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins to teach them certain things, we often perceive, that they know the names of a thouſand
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61559:27"/> other things, which we deſſeigned not to ſhew them: And what is moſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing therein, is, to ſee, when they are 2. or 3. years of age, that by the ſole force of their attention they are capable to find out in all the conſtructions which are made in ſpeaking of one and the ſame thing, the name, we give to that thing.</p>
            <p>They learn after this, with the ſame applic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion and diſcerning, the words which ſignifie the qualities of the things of which they know the names.</p>
            <p>At laſt, extending their knowledge farther, they mark ſome actions or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe ſame things; and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the ſame time thoſe that ſpeak of it, they, by virtue of their attention, and hearing repeated the <hi>words,</hi> which are mixt with the <hi>names</hi> that ſignifie the things or their qualities, diſtinguiſh thoſe that ſignifie action.</p>
            <p>Thus a child of a ſtrong and vigorous temper, ſeeing a Horſe that runs, ſeems to have a mind to fly after it, thoſe that intend to divert him, often asking him, Whether he ſeeth the Horſe: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61559:28"/> perhaps that word would be too hard for him to pronounce, in regard that Children do better pronounce all the words, that need only the Lips or the Gums to be well articulated, they give him a name convenient for it; and when by the effect he maketh to get to the Horſe, he is come near the pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of that word, he is led near the Creature, which he is made to flatter, by ſaying 'tis a fine, a good Horſe: which is often repeated as long as it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it ſelf to be thus careſſ'd. But if the Horſe begin to ſtir or ſnort, which may make one fear it might hurt the Child, thoſe that have a mind to take the Child away from it, preſently ſay, 'tis a <hi>naughty</hi> Horſe: And if that Child, when 'tis carried away, expreſſeth by crying it would ſtay, thoſe that hold it, fain a kind of fear, of which the Child knowing the outward ſignes in their looks, feels preſently the like mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which maketh it be contented to be removed from the Horſe: And whereas during all that while the word <hi>naughty</hi> is often repeated with demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61559:28"/> that make the Child more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, it conceiveth what this new word means, remembers it, and often repeats it his own way, ſo that, if after ſuch leſſons the ſame Child ſees an Horſe, it will repeat the word, which ſignifieth to him that <hi>Animal,</hi> and if in his approach to it he finds it gentle and content to be ſtroaked, he names at the ſame time the word that ſignifieth an <hi>Horſe,</hi> and that which ſignifieth its <hi>gentleneſs;</hi> but if it prance, the fear which the Child will have of it, will make it ſtrive to get away, and to name the word <hi>naughty</hi> as well as it can, after that which ſignifieth an <hi>Horſe,</hi> without tying theſe two words together by any <hi>Verb,</hi> that denotes any action.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here mention on the by that 'tis likely, that thoſe who made the <hi>Elements of the Grammar,</hi> made the like Obſervations. As the whole are of their method could not be deduced but from the Nature it ſelf, they muſt needs have conſidered, how Children learn to ſpeak; and I ſee that indeed <hi>their</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are nothing but an Imitation of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61559:29"/> 
               <hi>thoſe</hi> which Nature gives to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Grammarians</hi> teach the <hi>Words,</hi> that ſignifie <hi>things,</hi> which they call <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantives;</hi> then thoſe that ſignifie <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> which they call <hi>adjectives;</hi> and till they have well diſtinguiſh't thoſe two <hi>names,</hi> they teach not the words that ſignifie the <hi>actions</hi> of things, which they call <hi>verbs:</hi> wherein they follow alſo the ſons Nature gives to Children, who, as far as we can obſerve, do not apply themſelves to hearken to the words which ſignifie the <hi>actions</hi> of a thing, but when they already know the name of the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, and that of the <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi> which makes that thing pleaſe or diſpleaſe them: for 'tis alwayes accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this agreeableneſs, that they learn one thing rather than another.</p>
            <p>And to explain that by the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which I have already begun to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke uſe of; when the Child, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have ſpoken, knows well the name of the Horſe, and the names of the qualities, that make it pleaſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him, the deſire which it naturally
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61559:29"/> hath to extend its knowledge cauſeth it to obſerve the actions of the Horſe when it ſees it; and if at times we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that following the <hi>impetus</hi> of its temper, it gives ſigns of joy, when it ſees the Horſe run, we ſhall then ſay with ſuch out-cries as commonly do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company Joy, and by moving the Child in a manner like that the Animal moves in, that the <hi>Horſe runs;</hi> and this often repeated will make the Child conceive the word which expreſſes that <hi>action,</hi> inſomuch that it will not fail to joyn the word, which ſignifies the <hi>Horſe,</hi> to that which ſignifies its <hi>action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might, purſuing of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſhew, how a Child learns at length to ſpeak a whole language; but 'tis ſufficient to have exactly obſerved the beginnings of it, it being eaſie to underſtand the ſequel thereof. That wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch is only to be noted here, is, that it requireth much more time to teach them the power of <hi>Adverbs,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the words that ſignifie <hi>ſubſtances, qualities,</hi> and <hi>actions;</hi> becauſe it concerns not ſo much their conſervation to know that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61559:30"/> 
               <hi>more,</hi> or this <hi>leſs;</hi> that <hi>exceſs,</hi> or this <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> which are expreſs'd by the <hi>Adverbs,</hi> that are joyn'd to <hi>things, qualities</hi> or <hi>actions,</hi> as the <hi>things, qualities</hi> or <hi>actions</hi> themſelves do.</p>
            <p>It may alſo be conſider'd, that when they begin to take notice of <hi>the more, the leſs,</hi> of the <hi>exceſs</hi> or <hi>defect,</hi> they commonly expreſs it by ſome motion, or ſome pointing at bigneſs, ſmalneſs, according as things touch one another ſtrongly or ſlightly by their qualities or action.</p>
            <p>'Tis the ſame with <hi>Conjunctions</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>particles</hi> invented to connect things, or to ſeparate them. For, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren uſe them but ſeldom, and late; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they, following nature altogether, believe to have expreſſ'd the thing and its quality, when they have put the two words, that ſignifie them, to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And the ſame a Child does as to the <hi>action,</hi> which he expreſſeth by putting the word, which ſignifieth it, next the name of the thing, without being yet able to diſcerne that preciſeneſs of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61559:30"/> 
               <hi>times,</hi> or to obſerve that diverſity of <hi>terminations,</hi> which applying the word, that ſignifies one and the ſame action, to divers perſons and divers times, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Conjugation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might alſo ſhew, how a Child comes to know the <hi>term</hi> of actions; and laſtly we might draw from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural order, wherein Children learn to ſpeak, notions to judge, which of all the Languages are the moſt perfect: For doubtleſs thoſe which we ſhould find in their ordinary conſtructions to follow moſt that <hi>natural</hi> order, ſhould paſs for the moſt perfect.</p>
            <p>But ſince I only look here after the <hi>Principles,</hi> I am not to proceed ſo far to <hi>particulars.</hi> I deſire only, that by the way an important truth may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, which this example of Children evidently diſcovers to us, <hi>viz.</hi> That from their birth they have their reaſon entire; becauſe indeed this way of learning to ſpeak is the effect of ſo great a diſcerning, and of ſo perfect rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that a more wonderfull one cannot poſſibly be conceived.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61559:31"/>
            <p>If in the ſequel of age they appear without conduct, and almoſt without reaſon, it is to be conſider'd, that 'tis the knowledge of aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they are to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon upon, which they want, rather than reaſon. To which may be added, that the Cuſtoms of the World, which make up all the wiſdom of it, are often ſo contrary to what Nature, well order'd, would exact from men, that thoſe who are born, need to live many years, to learn things ſo remote from what Nature te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cheth. But alwayes 'tis manifeſt, that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Children is entire from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſeeing they learn perfectly the Langu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of the Countrey where they are born, and that in leſs time than Men of age need to learn that of a Country, where they ſhould chance to travel, and not find any body that underſtood theirs.</p>
            <p>By this time it is not difficult to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, why 'tis ſo eaſie for us to learn a ſtrange Language of a perſon that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it, and underſtands alſo ours: For then we can eaſily enquire after the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61559:31"/> name of every thing. By this means alſo we may learn many Tongues, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obvious, that after we have learnt the word, which ſignifies a thing in <hi>French,</hi> we may alſo learn, by what words the <hi>Italians,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations expreſs that thing: And what is remarkable, is, that when we have once agreed, that many words ſhall ſignifie one and the ſame thing, we ſo well joyn the <hi>Idea</hi> or the thought of that thing to each of thoſe words, that often we remember very well that the <hi>Idea</hi> of it hath been given us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remembring which of all thoſe words was employ'd for it: whence it comes to paſs, that when we are in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with perſons of different Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, whoſe Tongues we underſtand, we eaſily retain every news, and all what was ſaid upon the matters, that were ſpoken of, without remembring juſt the words nor the Language th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was made uſe of to give us thoſe images, which remain of them in us.</p>
            <p>This alſo ſhews very clearly, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, the diſtinction there is between
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61559:32"/> our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and the <hi>Words</hi> whereby we expreſs them: And as the principal end, for which I deſigned this Tract, is to ſhew this <hi>diſtinction,</hi> ſo I think I am not to omit in this place another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, which, in my opinion, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>that</hi> ſo evident, that 'tis not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibe to doubt of it.</p>
            <p>And that is, that when a man ſpeaks in publick, and hath for his Auditors many perſons of different Nations, the ſenſe of his words is not apprehended but by thoſe, who know the Language he uſeth, although the ſound of his words do equally affect all the reſt. But if the Soul were not diſtinct from the Body, and if <hi>Thoughts</hi> were not diſtinct from <hi>Motions,</hi> it would happen, that when the Brain of many perſons ſhould be affected in the ſame manner, they would all think the ſame thing at the ſame time, becauſe they equally have what in that matter depends from the Ear and Brain. But becauſe all have not agreed in this, that certain motions of thoſe parts ſhould ſignifie certain things, nor have joyned them to the images
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61559:32"/> they have of them, it happens, that one ſpeaks fruitleſly of thoſe things before them, and that they underſtand them not, though the words, employ'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them, ſtrike their Ear and Brain, as they do the Ear and Brain of thoſe that underſtand them.</p>
            <p>The ſame thing may alſo be ſeen in thoſe that ſtudy any Language. They often know in one inſtant the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a word, but know it no more in another; and yet they well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the word; and they have alſo the image of the thing, which it is to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them; but they have not yet ſo well joyned the one to the other, that that image returns to their mind, when the word is pronounc'd which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it.</p>
            <p>Although I am perſwaded, I have hitherto ſaid nothing but what is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on principles clear enough to leave no doubt, and that poſſibly they might be ſufficient to deduce other conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences from them, which might alſo diſcover to us ſome truths important e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; yet notwithſtanding I believe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61559:33"/> that to cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r up fully what remains to be ſaid, and even what hath been ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dy, it will be fit, before we proceed, well to diſcriminate all what is ſound in <hi>Speech</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s depending from the Body, from wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t there is in it, as depending from the Soul; and then to conſider what it borrows from their Union.</p>
            <p>Upon the account of the Body in him, that forms the Voice, it is to be conſider'd, that he hath <hi>Lungs,</hi> into which the Air enters by the Wind-pipe when the Muſcles of the Breaſt diſtend all the ſides thereof by their motion; juſt as Air enters in a pair of Bellows at the end, when 'tis expanded by ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the two ſides thereof.</p>
            <p>We are alſo to conceive, that as the wind, which iſſueth out of Bellows, when they are cloſed, would be capable to thruſt the Air as many different ways, as we ſhould put different pipes at the place where the wind comes out; even ſo the Air, which iſſues out of the Lungs, when the Breaſt ſubſides, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly thruſt, according as the Entry of the Wind-pipe is differently diſpoſed;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61559:33"/> which I enlarge not upon, becauſe I ſuppoſe, that 'tis generally known, that beſides many ſmall griſtly rings, ſerving to keep the ſides of the membrane, which forms that channel, by which the Air enters into and iſſues out of the Lungs, from approaching one another too near; there are three conſiderable ones, whereof one can ſhut it ſelf ſo cloſe, that when it is in that poſition, the Air cannot get out of the Lungs but with a great force; And ſometimes alſo it can ſo enlarge it ſelf, as that the Air may iſſue out very eaſily. But as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the greateſt and the ſmalleſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perture, of which it is capable, here is an infinite diverſity of other Apertures, of which every one makes a different impreſſion on the Air, we are not to think it ſtrange, that the Air which comes out of the mouth, is able to make ſo many different effects.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe alſo, that every one eaſily conceives, that the <hi>Cartilage,</hi> which ſerveth to modify the Air, is not deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the muſcles, that are requiſit to open it, to ſhut it, and even to keep it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61559:34"/> in certain poſitions, as there ſhall be need to make one and the ſame ſound laſt. Theſe Muſcles are diſpoſed in ſo wonderful an order, that 'tis not poſſible to ſee it without admiration. The other two <hi>Cartilages</hi> have alſo their Muſcles, and all things are ſo well ordered in that place, that one may raiſe or depreſs that Entrance, and open or cloſe it, and that either ſlowly or ſwiftly, yet ſo that the motion of the ſmall muſcles, which ſerve for ſome of thoſe actions, be not hindred by the motion of thoſe, that ſerve for others: Which informs us, that 'tis from the ſole diſpoſition of that place of the <hi>Wind-pipe,</hi> that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the ſounds depends.</p>
            <p>And 'tis to be obſerv'd, that if there were but that part, there would not be any difference betwixt the ſounds, it would make, and thoſe of a <hi>Flute,</hi> that is, it would make only uncertain ſounds, and no voices: but to give them a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain determination,</hi> the <hi>Mouth</hi> is ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd, that theſe ſounds coming to be tun'd, receive different terminations according to the different wayes it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:61559:34"/>
            <p>If for example you open the Mouth as much as you can in crying, you cannot form but a voice in A. And for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Character, which in writing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes that voice, or termination of the ſound, is called A.</p>
            <p>If you open your mouth a little leſs, advancing the lower jaw towards the upper, you'll form another voice termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in E.</p>
            <p>And if you approach yet more the jaws to one another, yet without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Teeth touch, you'l form a third voice in I.</p>
            <p>But if on the contrary you go to open the Jawes, and at the ſame time draw the Lips together at the two corners, the upper and the lower, yet without quite ſhutting them, there will be form'd a voice in O.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if you approach the Teeth, yet without quite joyning them, and at the ſame inſtant put out both the Lips by approaching them again, without quite joyning them, you form a voice in U.</p>
            <p>It is ſo eaſie to conceive, how the motions that are given to all the parts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61559:35"/> of the Mouth in each of thoſe formati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of voices, being mixt, there may be form'd voices, the termination whereof ſhall be intermediate between two of thoſe five voices; that I ſhall not ſtay to examine how theſe middle or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Voices are form'd, which are called <hi>Dipthongues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I believe 'tis neceſſary a little to examine, how thoſe motions of the Voice are made, that make thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Articulations</hi> of it, which in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting are expreſſed by the Characters cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Conſonants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some are articulated by the Lips on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; thus when we joyn our Lips with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out joyning the Teeth, we cannot form the voice A, but in disjoyning the Lips in ſuch a manner, as makes us articulate the Syll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble <hi>Ba,</hi> whereof the <hi>laſt</hi> letter expreſſing the termination of the Sound, that is, the Voice, is called <hi>Vowel;</hi> and the <hi>firſt,</hi> which marketh the manner how this voice is articulated, ſounding together with it, is called H. <hi>Conſonant.</hi> Whence, by the by we may ſee, that often the Voice may be good, without
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61559:35"/> being well articulated: For, the Lungs, which thruſt the Air, and the entrance of the Wind-pipe, may be ſo well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as to make the Voice very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and pleaſing; but in the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who ſhall have that advantage, the other parts of the Mouth may be ſo ill diſpoſed, that not being mov'd with eaſe, nor correſponding the one to the other with an intire juſtneſs, the Voice ſhall not be well articulated.</p>
            <p>What is ſaid of B. with the Voice A. may be ſaid of the ſame <hi>Conſonant</hi> with other <hi>Voices,</hi> without any difference in the articul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, which beginning al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with disjoyning the Lips is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the ſame, and receives not its different termination but from the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſite, which the parts of the Mouth put themſelves in, to form thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Voices.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conſonants</hi> P, and M. are formed as B. by disjoyning the Lips; but with this difference, that the Lips are to be only joyned to pronounce B. by open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; but they muſt be more ſtrongly cloſed and drawn inward to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61559:36"/> utter a P; and yet more cloſed and more drawn in, well to pronounce an M.</p>
            <p>The Letter F. is utter'd by joyning the under-lip to the upper-teeth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the former Conſonants are form'd by joyning both Lips together.</p>
            <p>The Conſonant V. is pronounced as the Letter F. with this difference, that you do more preſs your Teeth againſt the Lip for the Letter F, than for the Conſonant V.</p>
            <p>The Letter S. is pronounced by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the Under-teeth near enough to the Upper-teeth, and the Tongue near enough to the Palat, not to let the Air paſs, which is getting out of the Mouth, but by a kind of whiſtling: And the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Z. is pronounced after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, only with this difference, that for Z. we leave a little more ſpace to the air, by not approaching ſo much the Tongue to the Palat, and by ſo extending it that it may nearer approach the Teeth, than in the pronouncing of S.</p>
            <p>D. is utter'd by an appulſe of the top of the Tongue to the Gums of the upper-teeth; and T. by ſtriking with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61559:36"/> the top of the tongue againſt the place where the upper and lower teeth joyn.</p>
            <p>As for the letter N. it is form'd by ſtriking with the top of the tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the palat and the upper part of the teeth: And R. by carrying the top of the tongue to the upper part of the palat, ſo that the tongue being ſhaken by the air iſſuing forcibly, yields to it; and often returns to the ſame place, as long as one will have this pronunciation to laſt. And the letter L. is utter'd by carrying the top of the tongue between the place, where the letter N. and that, where R. is form'd.</p>
            <p>G. is pronounc'd by a gentle appulſe of the middle of the tongue to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward extremity of the palat; and K. by its appulſe to the ſame place with a little more force.</p>
            <p>As to X, it is a pronunciation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of S. and K. For C, it may be ſaid, that 'tis often pronounc'd like S. and frequently like K. The letter Q. is alſo pronounc'd like K.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the J. <hi>conſonant</hi> is pronounc'd by carrying the middle of the tongue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61559:37"/> towards the interiour extremity of the palat, with leſs force than in G, when 'tis pronounced with an A, or O, or V, For CH, it is a pronunciation of C, joyn'd to a gentle aſpiration; ſo that the ſyllable <hi>Ga.</hi> comes from the bottom of the Throat; the ſyllable <hi>Ka,</hi> from ſomewhat more forward; the ſyllable <hi>Ja,</hi> from a place a little nearer the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the palat, and the ſyllable <hi>Cha,</hi> from the very middle of the Palat</p>
            <p>I do not examine, why ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce certain conſonants better than others. For 'tis obvious, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility or difficulty of pronouncing comes only from the diſpoſition there is in the parts of the mouth, inſomuch that if the muſcles of ſome of them be well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and thoſe of others not, we ſhall pronounce the Letters well, where we have need of the motion of the parts, that are in a good diſpoſition; and we ſhall pronounce ill thoſe, where we have occaſion of the motion of parts, that are diſpoſed ill. Thus little Children will pronounce better the B. than P. D. and ſome others, where we need only the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61559:37"/> lips or ſome teeth, or the top of the tongue, than thoſe letters, to pronounce which there is required the uſe of the middle of the tongue, or where 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to redouble the tongue to the height of the palat, as the letter R; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the humidity of their Brain ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth their tongue too thick: whence we are wont, in ſpeaking to them, to alter the name of the things which they knew firſt, when there are letters which they cannot pronounce; and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Us, we mark to them their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother <hi>(Pere &amp; Mere)</hi> by words, of which the Conſonants are eaſie, being pronounced by the lips and teeth, or by the tip of the tongue.</p>
            <p>After we have taken notice as much as was neceſſary, How <hi>Sound</hi> is form'd; How 'tis terminated into Voices; and How articulated into ſyllables by him that pronounceth (to conſider nothing but the <hi>Body;</hi>) We are now to examine the effect it produceth in the <hi>Ear,</hi> it ſtriketh, and in the <hi>Brain,</hi> it ſhaketh.</p>
            <p>In regard that the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of the Ear is a thing commonly known, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61559:38"/> that 'tis ſufficient for every one to be perſuaded in the <hi>general,</hi> that it is an Organ diſpoſ'd to receive the air, when 'tis propelled by Bodies, which by touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another drive it from betwixt them, or repelled by hard Bodies, or iſſuing out of the Lungs of an Animal; I ſhall make no deſcription of it: I deſire only it may be obſerv'd, that as many different ſhakings there are in the Air, ſo many different ſorts there are of its paſſing into the Ear, and that according to thoſe diverſities it cauſeth a different agitation in the Membrane (ſtretch'd out in the bottom of the Ear) and in the Nerves anſwering thereto.</p>
            <p>It may alſo be judged by what we know of the conſtruction of Animals, even of Beaſts, that according as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation of the Nerves of the Ear is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, the Brain muſt be agitated in different parts; and likewiſe that 'tis alwayes according as thoſe different parts are agitated, that the ſpirits are differently diſtributed into the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>But all that is perform'd by a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61559:38"/> ſequel of the mechanical diſpoſition of the whole Body of every Animal, and even of every Beaſt, which being of a certain kind, that is, made for one thing or another, hath all what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to effect what the Author of Nature propoſed to himſelf in forming it: It hath the Brain ſo adjuſted (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its temperament) for all what may conſerve it, that if the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which can hurt it, move its Brain, 'tis alwayes after ſuch a manner, which maketh it to open in the places, whence the ſpirits may flow into the muſcles, which ſerve to make it retire from thoſe Objects; and if the Objects, which can benefit it, move its Brain, 'tis alwayes in ſuch a manner, as maketh it to open in the places, whence the ſpirits may be diffuſed into the muſcles, which ſerve to make it approach to thoſe Objects, ſo that if we ſuppoſe, that one and the ſame noiſe ſtriking the ears of two Beaſts of differing kind, do agitate at the ſame time their Brains, we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that that agitation being diverſly made in each, and in different parts of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61559:39"/> their Brain, according as that which cauſes the noiſe, ſhall be agreeable or contrary to it, it will alſo happen, that the courſe of the ſpirits being neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different in thoſe two Beaſts, one of them ſhall be carried far from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whilſt the other approacheth to it. Thus the howling of a Wolf may make a Sheep fly, but at the ſame time bring to him another Wolf.</p>
            <p>But 'tis neceſſary to obſerve here, that although the Art, whereby the Brain of Animals is compoſed, be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely varied, and that 'tis admirable herein, that according to their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent conformations 'tis always found ſo artificially diſpoſed, that thoſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures muſt neceſſarily and according to all the rules of the Mechanicks approach to what is naturally good for them, and retire from what is naturally noxious to them; yet it was not poſſible, that within the ſmall compaſs of their Brain there ſhould be ſo many differing ſprings, that they could have a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neceſſary, and always well ſuited to all ſorts of Objects.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:61559:39"/>
            <p>But inſtead thereof, their Brain is made of a ſubſtance ſoft enough, eaſily to receive new impreſſions, and yet conſiſtent enough to retain thoſe, which in ſome places thereof are made by certain objects, which being neither na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally good nor ill for them, do yet ſometimes occaſion conſiderable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or miſchief to them; and frequently thoſe traces, which at firſt were not in the Brain, remain there ſo well marked, that when the Objects, which cauſed them, preſent themſelves, the places, keeping the impreſſion, being more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated by them than the other, diffuſe thence ſuch ſpirits into the muſcles, as ſerve to carry the Animal nearer to or further from thoſe Objects, according as they have been found beneficial or noxious to it.</p>
            <p>Mean time, whereas there is much more danger for the Animal, to ſuffer the approach of the Objects, that can hurt it, than there would be in the not approaching thoſe that might do it good: at the time when there is yet no impreſſion in its Brain at the occaſion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61559:40"/> of an Object, if then it happen, that from a noiſe that Object begin to ſhake the Brain of the Creature, it will never fail to fly; eſpecially if the Air hath been agitated ſtrongly, or in ſuch a way that hath troubled the Brain,</p>
            <p>I believe there is no body, that hath not often felt in himſelf the effects of this ſurpriſe, and experimented how much the Will, which the Soul then hath to keep the Body in certain places, is controled by this natural Diſpoſition, which maketh all the Spirits and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles conſpire together to tranſport it far from thoſe places, where a noiſe is made; eſpecially when 'tis ſo great, that the whole Body is threatned to be there deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Every one may alſo have found, what force the agitation made in the Brain by a noiſe not ordinary, hath to make the Spirits, without one's thinking on't, flow into the muſcles, that ſerve to tranſport the Body out of the places where that noiſe happens.</p>
            <p>But ſince this is not yet the place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to examine, what the <hi>Soul's</hi> part is
<pb facs="tcp:61559:40"/> in <hi>Speech,</hi> we muſt, to finiſh the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of what ſhe borrows from the Body for the formation of a Voice, call to mind a <hi>Note,</hi> I have already made, which is, that the ſame Nerves which anſwer to the Ears, have bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches going to the Teeth, the Tongue, the Entrance of the Wind-pipe, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to all the places which ſerve to form or modifie the Voice; ſo that, following Nature's Inſtitution, the ſame ſhaking of the Auditory Nerves, which affects the Brain with the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cauſed by a voice in the Air, is alſo the cauſe, that the Spirits, which flow from the Brain into the Nerves of all the parts ſerving for the Voice, diſpoſe their Muſcles in a manner, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to the Impreſſion made by the Voice in the Brain, puts them into a ſtate to form a Voice altogether like it: And if it have been neceſſary, that the correſpondence, which is between the Auditory Nerves and the Brain, ſhould be ſuch, that when it ſhould be moved by the concuſſions of the air, <hi>that</hi> ſhould be done in different places of it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61559:41"/> to the diverſity of Noiſes, to the end that, following that diverſity, the Spirits might diffuſe themſelves into the Muſcles, that can carry away or ſtay the Animal, according as the cauſes of that noiſe are good or ill for the whole Body; It was no leſs requiſite, there ſhould be a ſufficient commerce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſame Auditory Nerves, and thoſe of the parts, that ſerve for the Voice, to bring it to paſs, that when a voice ſhould ſtrike the ear, the Muſcles of thoſe parts might immediately be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as they ought to be, to form ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfectly like it.</p>
            <p>And to manifeſt this neceſſity better, 'tis requiſite to make two reflections. The <hi>firſt</hi> is, that if it concern Animals, to have their Brain ſhaken by the noiſe of certain Bodies, before they approach too near them, that ſo they may avoid them; it concerns them likewiſe to have their Brain moved by ſome other Bodies, to the end that they may be carried towards them, when they are remoter from them, than is requiſite for their conſervation, or conveniency.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:61559:41"/>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is, that as, (conſidering only each Animal according to its <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi>) there is nothing more noxious to it, than thoſe of a contrary <hi>ſpecies;</hi> ſo there is nothing that can be more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to it than thoſe of its own kind.</p>
            <p>That being ſo, 'tis evident that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be ſo uſeful as this commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which is between the Ears and the parts ſerving to form the voice: For by this means the cry of one Beaſt ſhaking the Brain of another of its kind, it preſently comes to paſs, that not only it is carried towards that, which maketh the cry (according to what hath been ſaid) but beſides, the Muſcles of its Throat do ſo diſpoſe themſelves, that it makes at the ſame time a like cry, and this new cry ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Brain of that, which cried firſt, cauſeth the ſpirit to flow into the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which ſerve to carry it toward the ſecond; ſo that they ſooner meet, and may, according to the cauſes of the cry, that made them approach, draw from one another what may contribute to their conſervation.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:61559:42"/>
            <p>I very well know, that this neceſſity of forming cryes or voyces like thoſe, that have ſtruck the Ears, is not ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, that it muſt ſo fall out always; and that there are two caſes, wherein it happens otherwiſe even in Brutes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> is, when that Creature, whoſe Ear is ſtruck, and whoſe Brain is agitated by a Cry, is not of <hi>the ſame kind</hi> with that which maketh the Cry. For we know, by what hath been above deliver'd, not only that the diſpoſitions of the parts, which form the voice in Animals of different <hi>ſpecies,</hi> being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together different, that cannot come to paſs, but alſo, that what is the cauſe why a Brute makes a cry like that which is made by another of its own kind, is only that they may the ſooner come together in caſes of need, which they may ſtand in of one another.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is, that it may often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, even among Animals of the ſame kind, that the Brain of the one is mov'd by the Voice or Cry of the other after ſuch a manner, that it ſhall be more beneficial for that creature, whoſe Brain
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61559:42"/> hath been mov'd by that cry, to have the ſpirits flow into other Muſcles, than thoſe which ſerve to make a like voice. For example, if a <hi>Cock</hi> makes that noiſe he uſeth to make, when he meets with a grain of corn, it may be, that that noiſe ſtriking the ears of the Hens, will ſhake their Brain in ſuch a manner, as ſhall make them run to the place where that grain is, without forming a voice like that which made them come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: As alſo it may happen, that one Animal cries ſo, on the occaſion of a dangerous object, as that it maketh all the other of the ſame <hi>ſpecies</hi> run away, without forming any cry like it. But as often as a Brute is not preſſed by ſuch neceſſities, which do alwayes ſtronglieſt determine the courſe of the ſpirit in its Body, when its ear is ſtruck by a Cry; that communication betwixt the Ears and the <hi>Larinx</hi> maketh, that from the ſame place, where the Nerves of the Ear have made a motion in its Brain, the ſpirits do neceſſarily flow into the Muſcles of the <hi>Larinx,</hi> which diſpoſing it in ſuch a way, as is ſuitable to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61559:43"/> of the Brain do make the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal form a cry altogether like it.</p>
            <p>Thence it comes, that <hi>Birds</hi> excite one another to ſing: And in ſhort, this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce between the Nerves of the Ear, and thoſe of the parts ſerving for the voice, is in <hi>general</hi> ſo much the cauſe of the noiſe, which moſt Brutes make, that (provided they are not in any ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent need) when their ears are excited by ſome noiſe, the impreſſion it makes in their Brain, cauſes the ſpirits, that are not diverted another way, take their courſe to the <hi>Larinx</hi> to diſpoſe it to make a like noiſe. And as the noiſe which hath ſhaken their Brain, cannot alwayes be imitated by the voices, which they are capable to make accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the natural conformation of their Throat, they often return ſuch as are very differing. Hence it is, that <hi>Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Inſtruments excite Birds to ſing, yet their ſongs are ſo different from all that is play'd on ſuch Inſtruments. But to ſhew, that that proceeds only from the little conformity there is between thoſe Inſtruments and the diſpoſition
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61559:43"/> of the Throat of the Bird, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the imitation, we find that as often as there is a proportion between their throat, and the voices that ſtrike their Ears, they fail not to form at length ſuch as are like them.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Linets</hi> learn in time the note of <hi>Nightingales,</hi> the ſongs of other Birds, and what ever is play'd on Inſtruments; and they learn even, as <hi>Parrets,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſome of <hi>our</hi> words, becauſe they have the <hi>Tongue</hi> and <hi>Beak</hi> diſpoſed to articulate them. If they be long in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſongs of other Birds, or our words, 'tis becauſe the Nerves, which communicate from their ears to the muſcles of their Throat, Tongue, and Beak, cannot be ſo ſoon adjuſted to thoſe new ways of voices, as to cauſe their formation preſently; but it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears at laſt, that from the time that thoſe parts are capable to form thoſe voices, they do actually utter them.</p>
            <p>And we ought above all things to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the change which happens in them when they learn, is, that their Brain being divers times ſtruck in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61559:44"/> ſame place by the ſame Songs, or the ſame Words, the impreſſion thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſo ſtrong in that place, that the ſpirits which thence iſſue to flow into the muſcles of their Throat, Tongue and Beak, do at laſt diſpoſe them to repeat thoſe ſongs or words.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe to be well obſerv'd, that they never return the ſongs and words they have learnt, but when they are in no ſuch need, which diverts their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits another way; and if in thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities they form a cry or voice, 'tis ever the cry or voice of their kind; ſo that they form not ſtrange ſongs, nor utter human words, but when they want nothing, and when the ſpirits, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding or much heated, run, without any diverſion to their courſe, from the place of the brain, which thoſe ſongs or words have moſt agitated, to the parts that ſerve for the voice; except great care have been taken to give them none of the food they needed, but at the time when ſome body did ſing or ſpeak near them: for then the preſence of the food does not fail to excite
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61559:44"/> them to repeat the ſame ſongs or words.</p>
            <p>And to underſtand this well, we muſt conceive, that Brutes learn their cry from others of their kind, and that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the food is the cauſe of it. For their young ones, having at the ſame time their <hi>Ears</hi> ſtruck by the cries, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways made by their Dams at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſome food, which they have not yet the poſſeſſion of, and their <hi>Eyes</hi> alſo ſtruck by that food it ſelf; it muſt come to paſs, that the place of their brain which always receives thoſe two agitations at once, gets thence in time ſuch an impreſſion made in it, that the ſpirits taking their courſe from that place to the throat and the muſcles ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the voice, muſt needs diſpoſe them after ſuch a manner, as anſwering to the impreſſion of the brain, cauſeth thoſe young ones to make a cry like that of their Dam.</p>
            <p>But when they are brought up by men, and when <hi>Linets,</hi> for example, are bred in a Cage, and that in-ſtead of the cry of their Dam, it happens, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61559:45"/> in the preſence of the food, certain ſtrange ſongs or humane words ſtrike their ears; 'tis no wonder if thoſe words or ſongs (making impreſſion in the ſame place of the brain, whence that food ſhould have made the ſpirits to flow into the muſcles of the throat and beak, to cauſe them to make the noiſe, which birds make at the preſence of a food they hold not yet,) are cauſe that the ſpirits being otherwiſe directed, do alſo otherwiſe diſpoſe the muſcles of the throat, tongue and beak, of thoſe young Birds, and make them ſing ſongs and utter words inſtead of the cry, which they would have form'd, if their Dam had bred them: This muſt needs ſo happen; and even thoſe ſongs or words may then be call'd their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural cry or ſong, becauſe having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways accompany'd an action, that hath made ſo deep an Impreſſion on their brain, it cannot be, that that action ſhould move their brain, and the ſpirits ſhould not alſo flow preſently to the muſcles, which ſerve for that ſong or thoſe words. And likewiſe, if they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61559:45"/> have been put in a certain condition, or in a certain place to make them learn the better, they will ſooner repeat what they have been taught, if they be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the ſame condition and place, than in any other.</p>
            <p>'Tis eaſie alſo to underſtand, why it hath ſometimes happn'd, that a great noiſe, as that of a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> having at one blow ſhaken altogether the ear of a Bird, hath made ſo ſtrong an Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in his brain, that having ſtruck out all the others, the ſpirits have no more diffuſed themſelves towards his throat, than in ſuch a manner, as might diſpoſe the muſcles of the <hi>Larinx</hi> to return ſounds altogether like that of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet: And we muſt not wonder, if the paſſages, through which thoſe ſpirits flow to the throat, being more difficult to be moved, than the brain to be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the Bird remains ſometimes in a kind of ſilence for many days, before he renders that ſound; nor alſo, if that ſilence be perpetual, when the parts, which ſerve for the voice, are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to form a like one to the ſound,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61559:46"/> which hath ſo ſtrongly mov'd the Brain.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, there is no intelligent man, who after this diſcourſe ſees not, why an Animal being born <hi>deaf,</hi> muſt needs be <hi>dumb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which it reſults with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent evidence to a conſidering Man, <hi>firſt,</hi> That 'tis the Lungs and the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Wind-pipe, the mouth, the palat, the teeth, and the muſcles of all thoſe parts, which by receiving and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling, or in diverſly modifying the Air, is the cauſe, enabling us to form Voices, and to articulate them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That 'tis by reaſon of the communication, which is between the brains and the other parts of the body of every Animal, that it is diverſly agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by thoſe Voices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That in every Animal, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to form Voices, there is ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce from the ear to the brain, and from the brain to all the parts ſerving for the voice, that the ſame voice which ſhakes the brain by the interven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ear, diſpoſeth it alſo to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the ſpirits into the muſcles of thoſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61559:46"/> parts; which ſpirits putting them into a poſture anſwerable to the manner in which that voice did ſtrike the brain, make them form a voice altogether like it, if ſome preſſing neceſſity of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal diverts not the courſe of the ſpirits to another place.</p>
            <p>Which being once well underſtood, it will be eaſie to know a thouſand things, which commonly enough are not known touching the different effects of the cry and noiſe of Animals; which I mean not to explain more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, becauſe that all thoſe, who have attention enough to conceive the few principles, which I have laid down, will from thence draw all what is neceſſary to explain it, and becauſe thoſe that are not capable of ſuch an attention, would not conceive what I could ſay of it even in a more particular diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only ſtay to conſider here, that according to theſe Principles, Brutes need no Soul to cry, or to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by cries. For if they be toucht in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place, or their nerves ſtruck with force enough to cauſe a great ſhake in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61559:47"/> their Brain, 'tis ſufficiently eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that that action agitating the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, theſe muſt flow much more ſwiftly into the muſcles, and by this means the ſwiftneſs of thoſe that run inceſſantly to the heart, augmenting, muſt render the pulſes thereof more precipitate; which maketh it propel ſo great a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of bloud into the Artery of the Lungs, that this Artery being more diſtended than ordinarily, preſſeth the Wind-pipe, and maketh the air to be driven out of the Lungs with an impetuoſity anſwerable to that, whereby the bloud enter'd there.</p>
            <p>The ſecond effect of this quick agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ſpirits is, that at the ſame time they flow to the heart, ſome of them diffuſe themſelves alſo to all the other muſcles that are in a continual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as thoſe of the breaſt; becauſe, whereas the paſſages, through which the ſpirits are conveyed in thoſe ſorts of muſcles, are alwayes open by reaſon of the neceſſity of their continual action, the ſpirits cannot receive a new motion without preſently communicating it to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61559:47"/> thoſe Muſcles: which cauſeth thoſe of the Diaphragme and Breaſt preſs the Breaſt in ſuch a manner, as makes the air iſſue out with unuſual force; and ſeeing the muſcles of the <hi>Larinx</hi> are alſo ſtrongly agitated, the air thence getting out is beaten in a manner, which holds ſomewhat of that agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thus it may be conceived from the ſole diſpoſition of the Body, why a Brute cries: And to know how it may be <hi>moved</hi> by cries without having a Soul, you need but remember the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is between the brain, the parts ſerving for the voice, and all the parts of the body. For, if according to the difference of cries, the brains are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly moved, and if following that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of the ſhakings of the brain, the body is diverſly carried, we need go no further than their bodies, for a cauſe, why Brutes of one and the ſame kind are mov'd to come to one another by the cryes they make, and why their cryes often drive away thoſe of <hi>another</hi> kind. If we conſider only that they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61559:48"/> have a body ſo mechanically diſpoſed, that the ſole ſtructure of it may be the cauſe that 'tis carried <hi>to</hi> ſuch Objects, as may be good for them, and <hi>from</hi> ſuch as may hurt them; me thinks, that how wonderful ſoever their motions may ſeem to us, we cannot rationally impute them, and particularly their cryes, but to the conſtruction of their bodies; ſince, if we heed it well, we ſhall find in our ſelves, that the cries are not made but by the body alone. For indeed, if we cry, 'tis not becauſe we have a Soul, but becauſe we have Lungs and other parts, which can receive and force out the air with certain modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, if the Nerves of our Ears be mov'd by a voice, that is, by an air, which other bodies have agitated ſo, as that our brain ſhaken thereby, diffuſeth ſpirits into the muſcles of all the parts, whoſe motion can form a voice like that which mov'd it, that is, repell the air in a manner anſwerable to that which hath ſhaken it, it is upon no other account but that of our having a Body.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:61559:48"/>
            <p>Laſtly, if our brain, when 'tis ſhaken by a noiſe or voice, ſends the ſpirits rather into the muſcles, that ſerve to carry our body near <hi>to</hi> or far <hi>from</hi> thoſe which cauſ'd that Noiſe, than into the muſcles of the <hi>Larinx</hi> or of the other parts, ſerving to form a like voice, it is becauſe we have a Body. So that, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here be nothing found in Brutes but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he like effects, we cannot rationally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, that they have ought elſe but Body.</p>
            <p>But as for Us, we muſt avow (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we adſcribe to our bodies in what regards the cauſes and effects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he voice) there is alwayes ſomewhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccompanying them, which cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom the <hi>Soul.</hi> For as 'tis true (to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>general</hi>) that it would be ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have motions, for which our body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fit, and to receive the effects which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re wrought upon it by the various ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ects, that agitate the brain thereof, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſerve our body, for as much as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roportion and relation God hath put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wixt it and the other bodies of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld, gives it, without our thinking
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61559:49"/> on't, all what can maintain it in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſutable to its nature: So 'tis true alſo to ſay, that all <hi>that</hi> would be acted in us, and yet we <hi>perceive</hi> nothing of it, if we had nothing but the Body. But now, reflecting on what happens to us, when ſome noiſe ſtrikes the nerves of our ear, we ſhall plainly find, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that ſhaking of the nerves of the Ear, which continuing to the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal parts of the brain, doth there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitate the ſpirits, and makes them flow into the muſcles, ſerving to move ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole body near <hi>to</hi> or far <hi>from</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noiſe, there is always conjoyn'd a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> to every ſhake of our ear, or of the other parts of our body: And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times we even find in us a <hi>Will</hi> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to the motions which that noiſe excites in our body. And although ſometimes the impetuouſneſs of thoſe motions be ſuch, that we can hardly ſtop them in their carriere; yet 'tis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that that contrariety would not be found in us, if what renders us ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to <hi>Will,</hi> were not differing and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together diſtinct from what makes u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> capable to <hi>move.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:61559:49"/>
            <p>But of thoſe two things which we find in our ſelves, beſides <hi>Motion,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Perception,</hi> which we have, when-ever the nerves of our ear are ſhaken; and the <hi>Will,</hi> which we have by conſequent, <hi>to conſent</hi> to the motion, to which our whole body is excited, or <hi>to reſtrain</hi> it; me thinks the latter is ſo evidently diſtinct from our body, that none but very inconſiderate perſons can be without obſerving and knowing the diſtinction.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Perception,</hi> we have on the occaſion of the ſhaking, which the voice cauſeth in the nerves of the ear, though it be ſomewhat difficult to be diſtinguiſht from that ſhaking, becauſe it always accompanies it; yet 'tis eaſie to him, that is a little accuſtom'd to judge of the effects by their cauſes, to find, that the ſhaking, being a motion, cannot appertain but to our Body, and that the <hi>Perception</hi> being a Thought, cannot belong but to our Soul: And as we have found by other reflections, that the Union of our Soul and Body only conſiſts in this, that certain Thoughts
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61559:50"/> are ſo united to certain motions, that the one are never excited without the others be ſo too at the ſame time; we ought not to wonder any more to find, that the nerves of our ear ſhall never be ſhaken, but we ſhall preſently feel in our Soul a <hi>Senſation,</hi> or, if you will, a <hi>Perception</hi> anſwerable to the manner the nerves are ſhaken in; nor ought we to believe, that that <hi>agitation</hi> and that <hi>perception</hi> are one and the ſame thing, although they always accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one another.</p>
            <p>We are therefore to conſider two things in that we call <hi>Sound;</hi> one is the manner, in which the <hi>Air,</hi> ſtriking the nerve of our ear, ſhakes our brain; and the other is the <hi>Senſation</hi> of our Soul on the occaſion of that agitation of the brain. The <hi>former</hi> belongs neceſſarily to the Body, becauſe 'tis nothing but a Motion; and the <hi>latter</hi> belongs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to the Soul, becauſe 'tis a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewiſe in <hi>Speech</hi> there are two things, <hi>viz.</hi> the Formation of the voice, which cannot come but from the Body,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61559:50"/> according to what we have already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſ'd; and the ſignification joyn'd with it, which cannot be but from the Soul. So that <hi>Speech</hi> is nothing elſe but a voice, by which we ſignifie what we think. 'Tis true, you may alſo (as hath been already obſerv'd above) joyn your thoughts to other ſigns beſides the <hi>Voice,</hi> as to the characters of <hi>Writing,</hi> or to certain <hi>Geſtures,</hi> and that indeed all thoſe ways of expreſſing our ſelves are nothing but ways of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> (to take the word in a general and large ſenſe:) But then, becauſe the <hi>Voice</hi> is the moſt eaſie ſigne, the word <hi>Speech</hi> hath been appropriated to it, leaving to <hi>Characters</hi> the word of <hi>Writing,</hi> and to other ways of expreſſing our ſelves the word <hi>Signe,</hi> which is that of the <hi>Genus,</hi> common to all thoſe three <hi>Species's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be I have already ſaid enough of each of them, to make them to be ſufficiently diſtinguiſh't; but poſſibly alſo, ſince I have not examin'd them but on the ſcore of what they have common among themſelves, it may not be uſeleſs or tedious, to ſpeak of them
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61559:51"/> apart, that it may appear wherein they differ one from another.</p>
            <p>And to begin with that kind, to which hath been left the name of the <hi>Genus,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Signes,</hi> we muſt, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in a few words what may be known of it, take notice, that ſome of them are <hi>natural,</hi> others, that may be called <hi>ordinary</hi> or common, and others, that may be term'd <hi>particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>natural</hi> ones are thoſe, by which, becauſe of the neceſſary communion, which is between the paſſions of the ſoul, and the motions of the body, we know from without the inward diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſtates of the Soul. I have ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, that theſe motions are the ſame in all men. But yet we are to remember, that ſince we may purpoſely conſtrain them, or excite them at pleaſure, we are not to truſt them too much, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they ſignifie always what they ſhould ſignifie.</p>
            <p>The ſignes, which I call <hi>ordinary,</hi> are thoſe by which moſt men are wont to declare certain things, and thoſe are meerly of <hi>inſtitution:</hi> Some are more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61559:51"/> 
               <hi>univerſal,</hi> others leſs. E. g. When we will, without a voice, ſay that we <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> we give a ſigne with the head, quite differing from that which we make to ſhew, we <hi>conſent not:</hi> ſo we make certain ſignes with the hand to drive one away. And theſe kinds of ſignes are <hi>general</hi> enough; but thoſe, by which we declare our reſpect to one another, though commonly they be the ſame in a whole Country, yet they are very different in another.</p>
            <p>The ſignes I call <hi>particular,</hi> are thoſe in which a whole Nation or a whole Commonalty agrees not, but which are inſtituted 'twixt two perſons or a few more, to ſignifie certain things, which they would not have others to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Writing,</hi> there is none that's <hi>Natural,</hi> and 'tis by <hi>Art</hi> only, that men have found out the ſecret of it. As they ſaw, that they could make <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures</hi> and <hi>Voices</hi> to ſignifie what-ever they had a mind to, ſo they thought, that giving ſignifications to <hi>Characters,</hi> which the hand might form, thoſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61559:52"/> would be ſignes, which remaining for a long time after us, would make our thoughts known not only to thoſe that ſhould be far off, but alſo to them that ſhould be born a great while after them.</p>
            <p>And this hath been done divers ways. At firſt were uſed ſuch characters, whereof each ſignified <hi>a Thing;</hi> but this way was troubleſome, foraſmuch as men were to learn too many Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and to remember too many ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications; beſides that by that means there could only be ſignified <hi>Things,</hi> but <hi>Actions</hi> not conveniently.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, as it was obſerv'd, that all the diverſities of Speech proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only from the different ways of form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Voices, or articulating them, and that <hi>Five voices</hi> only, differently articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, or diverſly aſſembled, did form all the words; it was thought fit, to give a <hi>Character</hi> to each of thoſe Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: next there were inſtituted Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters to mark their <hi>Articulations;</hi> and the aſſembling of thoſe different cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters made <hi>ſyllables,</hi> which being
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61559:52"/> joyn'd together did compoſe entire words: ſo that diſpoſing thoſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters in an order like that we form the voices in, or the articulations which they repreſent, we remember the words, and thoſe words make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the things they ſignifie. Thus we ſee, that <hi>writing</hi> is a way of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> to the <hi>Eyes,</hi> which 'tis true demands more time to expreſs, but then it laſts alſo much longer.</p>
            <p>It hath likewiſe this other defect, that <hi>few</hi> perſons can ſee at the ſame time the Thoughts of him that uſeth it; but ſince <hi>that</hi> is made up by this admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable advantage, of being able to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the thoughts of the <hi>Writer,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſtance of places and times; it hath alwaies ſeem'd ſo great a convenience, that in ſeeking to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what is wanted, men have at laſt found the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Printing,</hi> that is, of making Characters of mettal or wood, which being once ranged, and charged with ink or colour, can mark all the leaves, needfull to gratifie many to read at the ſame time and in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſame thing.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:61559:53"/>
            <p>I do not diſcourſe here, that there are wayes of writing, that are <hi>ordinary,</hi> and others, called <hi>Cifers,</hi> which are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to certain people: Neither do I recite the way of expreſſing <hi>Numbers</hi> upon paper by characters that bear moſt commonly the name of <hi>Cifers;</hi> nor that of expreſſing <hi>Sounds</hi> by other characters called <hi>Notes:</hi> For all that is ſufficiently underſtood of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>As to the way of expreſſing ones-ſelf by the Voice, to which principally hath been given the name of <hi>Speech,</hi> we may ſay, that there are Voices <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> as thoſe that are put forth in Grief, in Joy, and in the other paſſions. But (as I have already ſaid of <hi>Signes natural</hi>) we muſt not always truſt thoſe voices, and they be often ſtrained, or uſed to make others believe, that we reſent what indeed we reſent not.</p>
            <p>There are other Voices, which men make uſe of to expreſs to one another their thoughts: Some are more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally receiv'd, as thoſe are which compoſe the Language of a whole Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, others are more particular, uſed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61559:53"/> by perſons, that agree amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of words altogether new to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify their thoughts.</p>
            <p>I have already taken notice, how we begin to ſpeak when we are little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; how one may learn a new Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and if there be any thing left to be ſaid on this ſubject, it will be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in this place, how he that learns a new Language may turn it into a habit.</p>
            <p>For that, we are to obſerve, that we joyn from the time of the firſt Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage we learn, the <hi>Idea</hi> (or image) of a thing to the <hi>ſound</hi> of a word; which is entirely upon the ſcore of the Soul. For the ſenſation, call'd <hi>Sound,</hi> and the <hi>Image</hi> of the thing, made to be ſignified thereby, are all from the <hi>Soul,</hi> as we have already made out. From the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's</hi> part there is a motion of the ſpirits and brain, which every voice excites, and an Impreſſion, which every thing leaves there: But that <hi>motion</hi> is alwaies joyned to that <hi>Impreſſion,</hi> as the <hi>Percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of every ſound is always joyned in the Soul with the particular image of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61559:54"/> this or that thing; ſo that when we will expreſſe the <hi>Idea</hi> of that thing, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive at the ſame time the <hi>ſound</hi> of the voice, which ſignifies it: then, on the occaſion of that <hi>Idea,</hi> and of the <hi>Will</hi> which the Soul hath, that the brain ſhould duly diſpoſe it ſelf to diffuſe the ſpirits into the parts, which are to form it; it comes to paſs, that it is ſhaken at the place where the impreſſion of that thing did remain, from whence the ſpirits flow into the muſcles of the parts, which ſerve for the voice, to diſpoſe them to form that which ſignifies what we have a mind to ſay: And as we have learned to joyn all thoſe things from our Birth that conjunction follows ſo cloſe the will we have to ſpeak, that we imagine that what is ſo readily done, muſt needs be much more ſimple; and ſince we ſee not any Engin much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but it performs its effects with much difficulty, we can ſcarce believe, ſeeing the facility there is in <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> that there ſhould need ſo many parts to be acted for that purpoſe: But we muſt accuſtom our ſelves by admiring
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61559:54"/> the ſtructure of our Body, to conſider that 'tis made by an incomparable Workman, who is inimitable. Beſides, if we are convinced, that the Union of the Body and Soul proceeds only from the perfect correſpondence, which God hath eſtabliſht between the different changes of the brain, and the different thoughts of the Soul; we ought not to wonder, that the one acts ſo eaſily upon the other, and that their actions do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways accompany one another ſo well, as long as God Almighty preſerves their Union.</p>
            <p>But in regard that this is one of the moſt important verities, that can fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſideration, it will not be amiſs, for the opening of all the difficulties thereof, to obſerve, that there are <hi>three</hi> kinds of Correſpondencies between the Soul and the Body.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> is <hi>natural,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is that neceſſary correſpondence, by which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſenſations riſe alwayes in the Soul, when certain motions are excited in the brain; as motions are excited in the Body, when the Soul hath a will to it.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61559:55"/> And this correſpondence cannot abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ceaſe but with our life, and that which wholly changes it, cauſeth death.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, there is a <hi>ſecond</hi> Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence 'twixt the <hi>Idea's</hi> the Soul hath of things, and the Impreſſions which thoſe things leave in the brain. This correſpondence, no more than the firſt, cannot change altogether; and whilſt the Soul is united to the Body, ſhe never has the <hi>idea</hi> of things corporeal, but their impreſſion is in the brain.</p>
            <p>But there is a <hi>third</hi> correſpondence between the <hi>Name</hi> of every thing and its <hi>Idea,</hi> which being only by <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> may be chang'd: but yet, in regard the <hi>ſound</hi> of the firſt name, men give to a thing, is a ſenſation, which the Soul ſtrictly joyns to the <hi>Idea</hi> of that thing; and ſince alſo the <hi>impreſſion</hi> of that name is found joyn'd to that of the thing in the brain, we find it a trouble to ſever them: Whence it is, that when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to learn a Language, we commonly explain by the <hi>firſt</hi> word, by which we nam'd a thing, the new word, by which
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61559:55"/> we intend to underſtand it in the tongue, we are learning.</p>
            <p>And there are even ſuch, whoſe brain is ſo diſpoſed, that when they learn a new Language, they always joyn to the words of that, which they already know, the words of the ſecond, to repreſent to themſelves what they ſignifie.</p>
            <p>Others, that have another diſpoſition of the brain, do ſo eaſily joyn the ſound of a new word in it ſelf to the <hi>Idea</hi> of the thing, that that <hi>Idea</hi> is equally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them by the two words, and they not obliged to think on the one to underſtand the other.</p>
            <p>Thus one may ſo well joyn one and the ſame thought to many ſignes, and to words of different Languages, that one may with an equal facility uſe both to expreſs it: But with a very little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration we may eaſily judge, <hi>by</hi> the pains we find in the beginning, to joyn the words of a new Tongue to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of every thing; <hi>by</hi> the neceſſity we are in, to joyn the image of a new word to that of an old, which made it to be underſtood; and even <hi>by</hi> the pains
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61559:56"/> we experience in pronouncing thoſe we learn, that <hi>Speech</hi> indeed depends upon the relation and correſpondency of many things, and that, if afterwards it becomes eaſie, 'tis only from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent compoſition of the brain, and the admirable, commerce between its moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and our thoughts.</p>
            <p>For the reſt, me thinks, if the Soul is oblig'd, whilſt ſhe is united to the Body, to joyn her thoughts to words, which cannot be heard nor form'd without the organs of the tongue and the ear; She might, if that union ceaſed, much more eaſily diſcover to every other <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> what ſhe did think. And truly if it be a pain to him that examins it, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, How the thought of a man that ſpeaks is joyn'd to the motion of his brain, and the motions of his brain to thoſe of the parts ſerving for the Voice; if it be difficult to comprehend, How that Voice, which is nothing but Air agitated, ſtrikes the ear, and is able by moving the brain to excite in his ſoul, that hears the ſound of the words, the <hi>Idea</hi> of the things ſignifi'd by them;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61559:56"/> if that, I ſay, is ſo hard to conceive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know, there is ſo ſtrange a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the nature of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and that of the Body, we cannot but eaſily comprehend, that if two Spirits were not united to Bodies, they would find leſs difficulty to diſcover to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother their thoughts, in regard there is naturally much more proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the thoughts of two like Spirits, than between the thoughts and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of two Bodies; and upon the leaſt reflexion made on the facility and clearneſs, with which one man conceives the thoughts of another by <hi>Speech,</hi> we ſhall avow, that a Soul might incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably more clearly and more eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the thoughts of another Spirit, if both of them depended not from the organs of the Body. For a ſpirit ſure ſhould more eaſily apprehend a thought which is a thing ſpiritual, than the ſigne of that thought, ſignes being things Corporeal.</p>
            <p>Thus I eſteem, that 'tis much more natural for ſpirits to manifeſt or to communicate to one another their
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61559:57"/> thoughts in themſelves, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſignes, than to ſpeak to one another, that is, to communicate their thoughts by ſignes, that are of a nature ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of Thoughts: The pains alſo which every one finds in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and on all occaſions where men impart their thoughts by ſignes or ſpeech, is not to comprehend what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thinketh, but to extricate his Thought from the ſignes or words, which often agree not with it.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo the ignorance of the ſignes and words, that is the cauſe, why men, bred in different Countries, are a long while together without being able to underſtand one another: But as ſoon as acquaintance hath afforded them all what's requiſite, readily to unfold what every ſign or word means, they find no more trouble to conceive their thoughts, of how different Nations ſoever they be. Which evidently ſhews, that men underſtand one another naturally; that the thought of one is alwayes clear to another, as ſoon as he can perceive it; and that, if there be men, who conceive
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61559:57"/> better than others what is ſaid, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of underſtanding comes from the ſtructure of their brain, which being ſo diſpoſed, as that the impreſſions, I have ſpoken of, are there more eaſily recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, better ranged, and more diſtinctly marked, makes the thoughts, anſwering thereto, to be alſo more eaſie, more conſequent and more clear; whereas thoſe who want that good conformation and diſpoſition of the brain, muſt needs be ſlower in conceiving, by reaſon of that neceſſary correſpondence and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the motions of the Brain and the thoughts of the Soul, whilſt ſhe remains united to the Body: But who ſeeth not, that that entanglement would ceaſe, if the Soul were ſeparated from the Body?</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo from the Fabrique of the brain and the other parts ſerving for the Voice, that the facility or difficulty of the expreſſion comes, and the pain, that ſome have to ſpeak, proceeds only from hence, that the parts of their brain, which anſwer to the thoughts of the ſoul, or thoſe that ſerve for the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61559:58"/> Voice, are ill diſpos'd; but not from their Thoughts, which alwaies explain themſelves clearly by themſelves, and would never be obſcure, if they were ſever'd from the ſignes, or the Voices, employ'd to make them to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and often not agreeing with them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, that indiſpenſable neceſſity, men are in, during life, to expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by words, is the cauſe that thoſe, who naturally have their Brain better diſpos'd in what may ſerve for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Soul; who have more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid impreſſions of every thing; who know to range them better, and who are accuſtomed to expreſs them in the moſt proper words; are alwayes thoſe, that ſpeak with moſt eaſe, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt agreeableneſs, and the beſt ſucceſs: inſomuch that if one will ſearch well after the phyſical cauſes of <hi>Eloquence,</hi> they will be all found in that happy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Brain.</p>
            <p>We know, that the <hi>firſt</hi> part of an excellent <hi>Orator</hi> is, to be able, eaſily to diſcern among all the things, that offer
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61559:58"/> themſelves to his Mind upon the ſubject he is to treat of, what his Auditors are to know thereof; to the end that he may preciſely tell them nothing but that; and 'tis evident, that unleſs he have a Brain diſpos'd to keep the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of every of thoſe particulars very diſtinct, he cannot make that due diſcernment of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> conſiſts in the well ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of all what is able to make the things, he deſigns to expreſs, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; ſo as what is the moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the moſt clear, and the firſt in the order of nature, may ſerve for a Light to clear up what follows, which of it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf might be more obſcure: And that cannot be, when the parts of the Brain are ill diſpos'd, or the courſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ill regulated; for then the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the things confounding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, often preſent to the mind at firſt, what ought not to be propos'd but at laſt; or elſe they are ſtirr'd with ſo much precipitation, that the mind can neither reflect upon the order of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, nor put it in its due place.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:61559:59"/>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> is, to know well, and to find eaſily the word, by which each thing is properly ſignified in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, he uſeth; and that depends from the <hi>Memory,</hi> which cannot be ſo faithful as it ought to be, unleſs the parts of the Brain be ſo well-ordered and in ſuch a temper, as keeps the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from confounding themſelves, and the <hi>idea's</hi> of one word from preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves, when he ſeeks for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>three</hi> things, that are abſolutely neceſſary in the deſign of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing,</hi> which is only the <hi>firſt</hi> part of <hi>Eloquence</hi> and theſe three things require a Brain of parts well order'd and ſtay'd and a Courſe of Spirits very well regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated; which, if there were no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, is very difficult to find.</p>
            <p>But then, when we come to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that for the <hi>other</hi> part of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which tends to <hi>move,</hi> we muſt know the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the Auditors, and their ſprings, in order to ſtrengthen or to change them, according as ſhall be requiſite for the end aimed at; and that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61559:59"/> the greateſt ſecret, well to expreſs a Paſſion to excite the ſame in others, is to feel it in our ſelves: we are obliged to confeſs, that for the good ſucceſs <hi>therein,</hi> it ſeems that the parts of the Brain cannot be agitated enough, nor the Courſe of the Spirits be too impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, if we did ſpeak to people, that were onely ſubject to <hi>Errour,</hi> and not to <hi>Paſſions,</hi> it would ſuffice to ſpeak the things in order, to explain them clearly, and to prove them in order to perſuade the Auditors of them; and for that purpoſe it would be ſufficient, to have the parts of the Brain well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and a temper not to be eaſily mov'd.</p>
            <p>But commonly we ſpeak to perſons, who beſides <hi>Errours</hi> are ſo ſubject to <hi>Paſſions,</hi> that they are not perſwaded, except you be <hi>equally</hi> furniſht with what is requiſite to <hi>inſtruct,</hi> and to <hi>move;</hi> and theſe two things depend from two diſpoſitions ſo oppoſite, that 'tis hard to finde men furniſh'd with Brains ſo temper'd and adjuſted, as to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61559:60"/> afford both thoſe perfections together.</p>
            <p>We find alſo, that generally all thoſe that are fit to <hi>inſtruct</hi> have a coolneſs, which makes them languid when they will <hi>move;</hi> and on the other hand, that thoſe who are very apt to <hi>move,</hi> have a fire in them, which maketh that the Auditors cannot conceive, but with difficulty, what they ſay to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct;</hi> Whereunto the Example which <hi>Cicero</hi> in one of his Diſcourſes relates of two Orators, agrees admirably well. He ſaith, that one of them was furniſht with a great clearneſs of mind, but was of a cold temper; and ſeeing that he had twice try'd to get ſome accuſed perſons quitted, without being able to make the judges reſolve for it, though he had perfectly inſtructed them; he beſought the <hi>other,</hi> whoſe <hi>genius</hi> was altogether different, to ſpeak on their behalf; which ſucceeded wonderfully well: And <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerveth, that that vehement <hi>Orator,</hi> ſeing there remained no more for him but to <hi>move</hi> the Judges already <hi>instructed,</hi> compoſed himſelf ſome hours before he went to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61559:60"/> to ſpeak of that matter in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate room with ſo much heat, that he was already in a ſweat, when he came before the Judges, whom he conſtrain'd, by the vehemency of his action, to grant him what the firſt could not obtain of them by the ſtrength of his reaſons.</p>
            <p>As often as I think on this caſe, I cannot but admire the advantages, which the <hi>Relator</hi> of it had in <hi>both</hi> the parts of Eloquence; and though I look upon him as the Pattern, which all thoſe that mean to proſper in this Art, ought to propoſe to themſelves, I avow, that he appears to me in-imitable. But he may ſerve as an Example to ſhew, that one and the ſame perſon may render himſelf cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to <hi>move</hi> and to <hi>inſtruct.</hi> I ſay, <hi>render himſelf</hi> capable; for I think not, that one may be <hi>born</hi> fit for both theſe things, if we conſider only, what we naturally find in every one; and I think that of the two Talents, which ſerve to make a man perfectly eloquent, there is one that may be ſupply'd by ſtudy, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he other is in our nature; but this is not reciprocal.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:61559:61"/>
            <p>And the better to examine this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, we are to obſerve, that thoſe who have a lively conception, have commonly the Paſſions violent, becauſe they have all the parts of the brain very ſubtile and exceeding moveable; but ordinarily they have but little memory, and if they find things eaſily, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them difficultly. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, thoſe that have the parts of the brain groſſer and more fixt, conceive things leſs and leſs eaſily; on the other hand, their paſſions are not ſo prompt; but for a recompence, they retain lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger both <hi>things</hi> and <hi>paſsions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis eaſie to ſee, that this latter ſort is capable to ſpeak, when the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is only to <hi>inſtruct;</hi> but if the ſpirits of men are to be managed, and not to be informed of certain things till they have been inſpired with certain paſſions thoſe latter will never get their end. And if ſometimes by virtue of obſerving other Orators, or by reading their Works, or by hearing them, they find out their Dexterities; they cannot imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them but in <hi>copying</hi> them in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61559:61"/> altogether reſembling thoſe which ſuch Orators have handled, without ever producing any thing matching the <hi>Original</hi> And even ſometimes, for as much as the Memory is all their excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and ſtrength, they borrow the very words of thoſe, whom they copy, and often they <hi>name</hi> their Authors to add ſome weight to the things, which they commonly deliver ſo little to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and alwayes ſo frigidly, that they would be intollerable, if they were not ſupported by ſome names in veneration among Great men.</p>
            <p>Orators of this ſort may exerciſe themſelves long enough; they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver arrive higher than to be <hi>Copiſts</hi> of ſome one entire piece; but they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gain the dexterity to reunite many ſtrokes of different Deſſeins, much leſs that of making new ones.</p>
            <p>Whereas thoſe that are of a contrary temper, having a lively and quick ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, know eaſily the ſtrength and weakneſs in a ſubject; they ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern what is to be declar'd, what to be hid: if they be obliged to ſay all, they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61559:62"/> know how to prepoſſeſs the ſpirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they propoſe what might be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to their Party, or diſpleaſe the Auditor; and when they form the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſein of their diſcourſe, if they imitate other Orators, 'tis only as far as it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to their argument: And to ſpeak truth, a Man of wit falls rather upon the thoughts of the Great Men that have been before him, becauſe <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſuggeſts to him what hath been ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, than becauſe he reads their Works.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, that that fecondity of the mind that maketh him eaſily to conceive and bring forth, may be the cauſe, that in certain things he will be too much car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, or diſpoſe them ill, or alſo not be able to retain them; but theſe defects are not without remedies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> may be ſupplied by a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent exerciſe of ſpeaking upon the ſubjects, in which a man finds he is wont to be moſt eaſily carried away, and by accuſtoming himſelf not to paſs certain bounds which he preſcribes to himſelf, or maketh his friends preſcribe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61559:62"/> to him; and 'tis not hard to give to one ſelf theſe reins, after a man once knows his propenſeneſs to be tranſported.</p>
            <p>To remedy the <hi>ſecond</hi> inconvenience, a man muſt accuſtom himſelf to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall his thoughts, and to order them well upon all the ſubjects he propoſeth to himſelf, of what nature ſoever; and as the way of <hi>declaring</hi> them is very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that of <hi>conceiving</hi> them, he muſt, to accuſtom himſelf to ſpeak well what he knows, often ask himſelf, how he would declare this or that matter, if he ſhould be obliged thereto; in what manner he would handle the <hi>ſame</hi> ſubject before a great multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or before a leſs Aſſembly; what would be ſaid of it, if ſpoken before perſons of power and honor, or before his Equals; and to render this practiſe more uſefull, he is to examine when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſpoken in publick, wherein 'tis they have ſucceeded well, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in been deficient; and even to endeavor, after having found the cauſe of their failure, to make up the ſame diſcourſe better than they did; and to continue
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61559:63"/> theſe Exerciſes until one's mind be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd well to digeſt all ſorts of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>third</hi> Inconvenience, which is that of the Memory, ſeeing that that cannot be defective, but in not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to us the <hi>things,</hi> or in not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing us with the <hi>words;</hi> there is a remedy for the firſt defect, by putting the <hi>things</hi> in ſo natural an order, that the one muſt needs make you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the other by the connexion they have together; and then, after a man hath form'd the deſſein, and order'd all the parts of a diſcourſe, he muſt often revolve and repeat it with himſelf, to be accuſtomed to it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Words,</hi> we are not to fear their eaſie occurring to us for ſpeech, when the matters are preſent to our Mind, if ſo be we are accuſtomed to ſpeak. And for that purpoſe, a man muſt impoſe upon himſelf the neceſſity of ſpeaking upon all ſorts of ſubjects, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom himſelf, by writing, to vary and turn them every way, and alwayes to chuſe the moſt difficult or the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61559:63"/> matters. For when by the force of ſearchng a man can find ways to make <hi>thoſe</hi> things to be underſtood, he hath almoſt no difficulty to find words and expreſſions in all other ſubjects, that are more ordinary, and which the various neceſſity of Life render more common.</p>
            <p>After we have thus examined, How much Eloquence depends from mens Temper, and how <hi>that</hi> may be corrected or perfected by Exerciſe; it will not be amiſs to conſider, That there is no greater Enemy to true Eloquence, than <hi>Lying:</hi> And as Eloquence is a means not only to expreſſe what we think, but alſo to oblige <hi>others</hi> to think as we do, it ought never to be employed but to manifeſt <hi>Truth,</hi> or to make it to be embrac'd and follow'd; and he that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes it to excite in others unjuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, or to make them believe things that are falſe, commits the moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous of all treacheries. For tell me, I pray, if human ſociety be not entertain'd but by <hi>Speech,</hi> is it not a violation of the moſt ſacred right that is amongſt men,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61559:64"/> to employ, for the leading of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to error, or for perſuading them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, ſuch endowments as ought to ſerve only to make them know what's <hi>true</hi> or <hi>just?</hi> If this were ſeriouſly thought on, there would be much more ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; eſpecially when men ſpeak in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, where the leaſt diſguiſes may draw after them very dangerous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces For the reſt, me thinks, that to make us accuſtom our ſelves to ſpeak nothing but truth, 'tis a powerful motive, often to repreſent to our ſelves that we have not the facility to expreſſe our ſelves, but becauſe God Almighty, to whom we owe our thoughts and the motions of our tongue, is very willing to excite the one, when we will make known the other. Me thinks, 'tis in a manner impoſſible for one, that makes often this reflexion, to lye. For, I pray, if we be convinced, that God is not ſubject to error, nor to a lye, nor to any iniquity, which alwayes follows it ſo cloſe; how can we employ Signs and Voices, which are not form'd but by his power to do that, which diſpleaſeth
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61559:64"/> him moſt? I admire, that a Heathen came to know this truth ſo far, as to ſay, <hi>That no man could be eloquent, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he were honeſt;</hi> and that <hi>we</hi> ſhould have ſuch contrary ſentiments.</p>
            <p>But not to mix here <hi>Morality</hi> farther than 'tis ſutable to a Diſcouſe of <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Philoſophy, it will be to our purpoſe to examine in this place, whence it is, that not only an <hi>Orator</hi> ought to be a man of integrity, but alſo that he cannot be perfectly eloquent, unleſs he be ſo? And this is not hard to conceive: for, if it be agreed on, that to be perfectly eloquent, a man muſt know the Art to inſtruct his Auditors, and that of raiſing or allaying Paſſions, according as it ſhall conduce to the end, that is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; we muſt alſo agree in this, that an <hi>Orator,</hi> that ſpeaks the contrary to what he knows, will not ſo eaſily find words to expreſſe it, as if he ſpoke the truth; and if to avoid miſtaking, he ſtudies what he is to ſay, it muſt be acknowleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that his Diſcourſe, which will be but a piece of Memory, can never have that grace nor force, which is found in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61559:65"/> that of a perſon, who having learnt to ſpeak well, and ſpeaking what he thinks, fears not, he ſhould miſtake.</p>
            <p>Again, it muſt be granted, that if he, that is not an honeſt man, will excite in others the motions and paſſions, which really are not in himſelf, 'twill always go off coldly, to expreſs paſſions ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and if, to ſurmount the effect of that conſtraint, which appears when a man will refrain his own motions to fain others, he will blot out all the ſtrokes and the little motions, by which his Countenance, Eyes, and Geſture would ſhew the contrary to what his Words do expreſs, he muſt ſo exceedingly ſtrain, that not only he loſes the grace, without which a man cannot pleaſe nor perſuade, but alſo renders himſelf odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and is ſo far from exciting in others the motions which he hath not in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he begets horror in all thoſe, who perſwade themſelves, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed feels the <hi>violence</hi> of the paſſions, wherewith he appears to be moved.</p>
            <p>In a word, 'tis evident, that there is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſuch a relation between the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61559:65"/> of men, and the Signes and Words uſed to expreſs them, that one and the ſame perſon can never tell a Lye ſo gracefully as a Truth: And as a man cannot be very eloquent, when he conſtrains to <hi>ſay</hi> what he doth not <hi>think,</hi> or to expreſs what he feels not; 'tis impoſſible to be very eloquent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs one be very ſincere and honeſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it belongs only to a man of integrity to ſpeak n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kedly what he thinks; his motions are ſo juſt, that he needs not to put on any conſtraint; beſides, the Truth, which accompanies all his words, and that love of Juſtice, which animates all his motions, give ſo much weight and grace to his action, that 'tis in a manner impoſſible to reſiſt it; and which is the chief, we are eaſily carried away by the motions of a man, whom we believe to be Virtuous: and when he, that ſpeaks, hath the advantage of exciting in others the ſame paſſions which himſelf reſents, as he is ſoon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of their thoughts, ſo he ſoon ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders their judgment favorable to what he aims at. And ſince we ſee, that thoſe,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61559:66"/> whom a like diſpoſition of body maketh lyable to the like motions, have ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the ſame ſentiments about the ſame things, we may juſtly believe, that the faireſt means to gain others to the ſame opinion with ours, is to raiſe motions in them altogether like ours. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (which particular cannot be too often repeated) as long as our Souls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main united to our Bodies, all our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will be ſo conſonant with our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, that we ſhall never be able to inſpire the one but by the other.</p>
            <p>This reflexion maketh me think, that as we can conceive Spirits not united to Bodies, if there be eloquence amongſt them, <hi>that</hi> cannot be by the means of <hi>Motions,</hi> becauſe they are not capable of them: But ſuppoſing, that thoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are in that ſtate of liberty, wherein they can determine themſelves to this or that thing, 'tis eaſie to conceive, that if one of them, being more enlightned than others, hath a paſſion for a thing, which a meer ſpirit is capable to have a paſſion for, (as for example, for his own glory) he may put his thoughts, which
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61559:66"/> he ſhall manifeſt to others upon that ſubject, into an order which ſhall appear ſo excellent, that it ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite in ſome the ſame paſſion which he reſents; and on the other hand (to keep to the ſame example) a Spirit yet more illuminated and better inclined than the former, may make thoſe, who might have fallen into that error, to conceive, that, whereas that Glory can appertain to none but the <hi>Soverain Power,</hi> 'tis a folly for any one to pretend to it, when he is not God.</p>
            <p>It might after the ſame manner be conceived, how meer ſpirits might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire one another with divers ſentiments touching all ſuch things for which they were capable to have paſſions, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (as hath been ſaid) that they were in a ſtate of chuſing one of two.</p>
            <p>But to draw from this notion no more than may ſerve for my intent, it is to be conſidered, that if for ſpeaking a man needs the motion of the parts that ſerve for the voice, and if for hearing there is need of the agitation of the parts, that ſerve for Hearing; there needs nothing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61559:67"/> between two Spirits, to communicate their thoughts to one another, but to <hi>will</hi> it: And ſince we find, that the thought of one man is eaſily underſtood by another, from the time that the firſt hath ſpoken, that is, from the time that by the motions, which ſerve to beat the Air, he hath moved the Ear of him, to whom he will have his thought known; 'tis alſo eaſie to apprehend, that if two Spirits, who depend not from the Body in their operations, will diſcover to one another their thoughts, they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do but to <hi>will</hi> it: There is, me thinks, much leſs difficulty to conceiv the one than the other (as I have already obſerved:) For in <hi>Speech</hi> there are two things, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> to communicate one's thoughts, and the <hi>Motions</hi> by which they are communicated; but thoſe Motions have ſo little affinity, in themſelves, to the thoughts, that it ſeems very ſtrange, how a thought can be ſo well united to a motion, as that the one ſhould be an occaſion to know the other; whereas in the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which two Spirits make to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61559:67"/> of their thoughts, there needs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the <hi>Will</hi> to communicate them; and Spirits being of one and the ſame nature, 'tis evident that one <hi>Thought</hi> may much eaſier be the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of another thought, than <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But next, what hath been ſaid of the Communication of two <hi>meer</hi> Spirits, ought to be ſaid of the commerce that may be betwixt a Spirit united to a Body, and one that is not. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly what incapacitates two men to communicate their thoughts to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other without motions, is, that they have Bodies, and that the one cannot be advertiſ'd by the other but by the motions occaſion'd by the Body, to which the Soul is united: But ſuppoſing that one of the Spirits have no Body, it is capable to render it ſelf preſent by its very thoughts to that which hath a Body, as it doth to that which is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of a Body; and reciprocally that Spirit, which is united to a Body, will be able, without the intervention of the Voice, to expreſs its thoughts to every Spirit that is Body-leſs.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:61559:68"/>
            <p>Mean time we are ſo accuſtom'd to judge of all things, by thoſe we ſee, that ſince men make uſe of a voice, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eaſily underſtand one another, we raſhly judge, that it would be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to two Spirits mutually to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their thoughts: And ſome judge it even impoſſible, that a Spirit, deſtitute of Body (for example, an <hi>Angel</hi>) ſhould communicate with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> But 'tis evident, that that proceeds only from the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation of our Spirit, who maketh no reflection on what befals him in the communication, he hath with the ſpirit of another Man. For if he did conſider, that the beating of the Air, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, which ſerve to make him underſtand the thoughts of the perſon that diſcourſes with him, have nothing in them reſembling thoſe thoughts; he would more wonder, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands him, than he wonders, when one will perſwade him, that two <hi>Angels</hi> ſpeak to one another, or that even one <hi>Angel</hi> can converſe with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> without the aſſiſtance of a voice.</p>
            <p>I cannot in this place forbear to take
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:61559:68"/> notice, how much the reflexion, we make on what paſſeth <hi>within us,</hi> is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to make us judge aright of what is done, or at leaſt may be done <hi>elſewhere.</hi> And the Example I draw from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, after which we converſe with men, is ſo proper to make it to be conceived, what might paſs betwixt Spirits deſtitute of ſuch Bodies as we have, and even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe Spirits and Us, that, the thing being well examin'd, there will be found no other difference between thoſe two ſorts of Communications, but that that, which is between Man and Man, will prove the more difficult to conceive, in regard it is made by the means of <hi>Motions,</hi> which are quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from <hi>Thoughts,</hi> whereas that, which we may have with meer Spirits, is leſs ſenſible, becauſe 'tis perform'd without any of thoſe motions, which render as 'twere ſenſible to us the thoughts of the men, whoſe voice ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth our Ears.</p>
            <p>And this may be alſo the cauſe, why we are inform'd, that when Spirits would give any important advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61559:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> to Men, they borrow'd Bodies, and form'd Voices like thoſe of Men. But thoſe Extraordinary things are not to hinder us from conceiving, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally we can communicate with <hi>meer Spirits</hi> more eaſily than with <hi>Men.</hi> So that if Faith teaches us, there are Spirits not united to Bodies, and that he, who hath created them as he hath us, having committed to them the care of condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting us, they are always preſent to our Spirit to direct it without conſtraining it; there is nothing in that, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thoſe things, we think we know beſt. For in ſhort, as we conceive, that the communication between two Men is made by <hi>Speech,</hi> that is, by a <hi>Will</hi> to expreſs what they think, and by the <hi>motions</hi> anſwering to that will, we may alſo, me thinks, conceive, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of two Spirits may be made by the <hi>ſole Will</hi> of manifeſting themſelves to one another; and that if a meer Spirit communeth with a Man, though that be in a way leſs ſenſible than is that of ordinary Words, yet 'tis after a manner intelligible, which may inſenſibly give
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61559:69"/> him the thoughts, he needs for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; which in a word, is, to inſpire him. Even ſo may we eaſily conceive, that God, who cauſeth our Spirits to move Bodies, can (if need be) give to an Angel the ſame power to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be underſtood by ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Now, me things, I ſee, what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meant by the word <hi>Inſpiration;</hi> and I believe, I am not deceived, when I ſay, that 'tis by that means only, that thoſe thoughts may come into our mind, which have no affinity to any of thoſe, that naturally are in our Soul, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have a Body.</p>
            <p>Next, I ſee, that we know no more the Spirits of any of all thoſe men, that ſpeak to us, when they inſpire us with their thoughts, than thoſe <hi>meer</hi> Spirits, which I think capable to inſpire us bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoughts. And as the new thoughts, which come into our mind by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation we have with men, are a ſure teſtimony to any of us, that they have a Spirit like ours, we are to take the new thoughts coming in to us (without being able to find the cauſe of them in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61559:70"/> our ſelves, or impute it to the diſcourſe of men) for an aſſured teſtimony, that there are yet other Spirits, that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire us with them.</p>
            <p>I find alſo, that the cuſtome of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the thoughts of other men by geſtures and the voice, maketh that way to affect us more, than the things, which are inſpired us without it. But if I heed it well, I ſee, that we do not more know the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rits of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th t ſpeak to us, than t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rits th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> us. A like Air, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of him, that diſcourſes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſtriking our ears, exciteth, upon the agitation of the Brain, ſounds in our Soul, and at the ſame time the images or concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we have joyned to thoſe ſounds: But in truth, neither that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled Air, nor any thing of what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into the Body from him that ſpeaks to us, is his thought; and if we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſon to believe him to have thoughts, 'tis only becauſe we feel, that he excites new ones in us. But if all the reaſon, we have to believe, there are Spirits united to the Bodies of the men
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61559:70"/> that ſpeak to us, is, that they give us of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten new thoughts, ſuch as we had not, or that they oblige us to alter thoſe we had; can we doubt, when new thoughts come into us, that are above our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral light, and contrary to the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the Body may excite in us, can we, I ſay, when no men inſpire us with them, doubt of their being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired us by other Spirits? I judge, we cannot reaſonably; and the cuſtome, we have to receive them by the means of Speech, which is a ſenſible way, ought not to make us diſadvow thoſe, that are inſpired us by a way different from that of the ſenſes.</p>
            <p>I know alſo, that if we be free to hide our thoughts, whilſt our Soul is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to a Body, we might have the ſame liberty, if it were ſeparated from it; and that in ſome manner that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would yet be greater, in regard that often when we ſpeak to a perſon, the ſignes and the voices, by which we expreſs our ſelves, may be perceived or underſtood by a Third, to whom we would not diſcover our thoughts;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61559:71"/> whereas a pure Spirit, who is not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to make uſe of thoſe external ſigns, can manifeſt his thoughts to the Spirit he will inform, ſo as no other ſhall know of it.</p>
            <p>In effect, in that ſtate we now are in of diſcovering our thoughts, we do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to <hi>Will;</hi> and although that <hi>Will</hi> be joyned to motions, which fail not to be in certain parts of our body as ſoon as we need it for the ſignifying our thoughts; yet notwithſtanding our ſouls are not the cauſe of thoſe motions (according to what we ſhewed in our 4th Diſcourſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In his book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titl'd,</hi> Le Diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement du Corps &amp; de l' Ame.</note>) and they do nothing elſe to expreſſe themſelves but to <hi>Will,</hi> ſo that as long as they are united to our Bodies, we cannot expreſs the thoughts coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our mind but by moving the Tongue, the Throat and the Mouth; this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is impoſed on us by that union: But as ſoon as there ſhould be no ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to borrow motions for expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what we think, there would need no more to make other Spirits under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61559:71"/> it, but to <hi>will</hi> that they ſhould underſtand; and if we would have it hid from them, there would need no more than <hi>not</hi> to <hi>will</hi> that they ſhould know it.</p>
            <p>I have elſewhere deliver'd the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by which it appears, that all the action of the Soul conſiſts in <hi>willing,</hi> and I think I have ſufficiently made it out, that all what depends from Her, is, to determine herſelf to one thing or another, ſo as I ſhall not need here to repeat any thing of what I have ſaid on that ſubject: But it will not be amiſs to take notice in this place, that although God do not make us conceive, what is the ſubſtance of our Spirits, nor how they <hi>will,</hi> that is, how they determine themſelves; yet we know clearly, that we have a Spirit, and that our Spirit hath the power of determining it ſelf. But now, as we are aſſured, that we ſpeak not our thoughts but when we pleaſe, we ought to believe, that if we were in a ſtate to need ſignes and voices no more, we might then by our <hi>Will</hi> alone diſcover or hide our thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:61559:72"/>
            <p>We are alſo to remember, that 'tis not more difficult to conceive, that <hi>then</hi> we ſhould make our thoughts to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by other Spirits, than to conceive, that the ſpirit of another man ſhould apprehend, in the preſent ſtate, what we think, when we expreſs it by voice or by ſignes.</p>
            <p>For the reſt, when I ſay, that Souls emancipated from the Body might hide or manifeſt their thoughts to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>that</hi> is to be underſtood, if they had the ſame reaſon to hide their thoughts, they have now in the preſent ſtate. But 'tis apparent, that, if they ſhall be happy, as they will have no thoughts but for the Glory of their Maker, ſo they will be glad that all the Spirits ſhould know them; and if they for ever loſe his grace, they will have only ſuch thoughts, which being to ſerve to publiſh the effects of his juſtice, will be known to all the Spirits.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we ought to remember, that according to what I have deliver'd of the Action of Souls and Bodies, in the <hi>fifth Diſcourſe</hi> of the <hi>firſt part,</hi> we ſay,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61559:72"/> that one Soul acts upon another Soul, as often as one hath new thoughts upon an occaſion given by the other; even as we ſay, that one Body acts upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Body, as often as one Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives ſome change upon occaſion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded by the other: And as I have ſhewn, that a Body never gives any motion to a Body, but only for as much as their meeting together is an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Divine Power,</hi> which moved one, to apply it ſelf to the other; We are alſo to conceive, that when one Soul will make known to another Soul what ſhe thinketh, that happens foraſmuch as Almighty God brings it to paſs, that according to the will of the one, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comes to know it: And even as the <hi>Will</hi> we have, that our Body be mov'd, does not make it move, but is only an occaſion to the <hi>Firſt Power</hi> to move it after ſuch a manner as we deſire it ſhould be mov'd; ſo the <hi>Will</hi> alſo, which we have, that a Spirit ſhould know what we think, is an occaſion to that <hi>Power</hi> ſo to order things, that all may be diſpoſed in ſuch a way, as that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61559:73"/> that Spirit may underſtand it.</p>
            <p>Thence it neceſſarily reſults, that 'tis as impoſſible for our Souls to have new perceptions <hi>without God,</hi> as 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the Body to have new motions without Him. And 'tis evident beſides, that our Souls, which depend from Him for their Being and for their Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, depend not at all from Him for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of their Will,</hi> whereof he leaves the determination altogether free. And I dare deliver it as a thing that will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear manifeſt to all men of good ſenſe, who ſhall attentively conſider it, that as the Body is a ſubſtance, to which <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion</hi> belongs naturally, ſo that it would, as to effects naturall, ceaſe to be a Body, if it ceaſ'd to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; even ſo the Spirit is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to which the power of deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining it ſelf doth ſo naturally apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that it would ceaſe to be a Spirit, if it ceaſ'd to <hi>will;</hi> and God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath made it thus, that he might be loved by it. Which appears ſo evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if he had not declared it by ſo many miraculous teſtimonies of his
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61559:73"/> tenderneſs, which goes ſo far as to ask of us our Heart, that is to ſay, our Love; we ſhould be altogether perſwaded, that He will be the object of our <hi>Will</hi> in this World, by this only conſideration, that there is no object ſo great, but it can embrace it.</p>
            <p>As to the power of <hi>knowing,</hi> perhaps he hath not given us that ſo great, at leaſt not in this World. But 'tis certain, that we have knowledge enough, as not to fail, if we uſe well the light we have, and the power we are endowed with, of judging of nothing, but after we do well know it. For, God gives us all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight we need; we have <hi>idea's</hi> very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, to know the things of Nature as much as 'tis uſefull to know them, ſince we can, when we uſe prudence, diſcern wherein every one is beneficial or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to us: And although, according to what I have already obſerv'd, he afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us not the advantage to know the very ſubſtance of things, yet he ſo well diſcovers to us, wherein they can hurt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r profit us, that to uſe it aright, we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly to will it.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:61559:74"/>
            <p>As for thoſe things, which are <hi>above Nature,</hi> although they infinitely ſurpaſs our knowledg, yet we have very diſtinct notions of the Reaſons, why we are not able to <hi>conceive</hi> them, and of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alſo, why we are to <hi>believe</hi> them. For if on the one hand in the doctrine of Faith there are things to be found, that are beyond our natural light; we have on the other, ſuch evident ſignes of the Obligation for us to ſubmit our Spirit to his Authority, who propoſeth them to us, and ſo great convictions of our unableneſs to comprehend all what is; that we have cauſe to take all, what comes to us from thence for infallible Truth; in a word, for Notions which we hold from <hi>Grace;</hi> and from which, as well as from thoſe which we hold from <hi>Nature,</hi> we may deduce all the Concluſions that may ſerve to regulate our Belief, and the Conduct of our Life, ſo that we are guilty, when by inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or obſtinacy we deviate from thoſe Rules.</p>
            <p>But without inſiſting on the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61559:74"/> of all the great Truths; that might be collected from this whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I think it will become me to conclude, after I have conſider'd all the ſeveral wayes, whereby Thoughts may be communicated, which is properly what we call <hi>Speaking,</hi> and which I had propoſed to my ſelf to examine.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>John Martyn</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> a little without <hi>Temple-bar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory of the Royal Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> for the Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Natural Knowledge, by <hi>Tho. Sprat.</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Philoſophical Tranſactions, giving ſome Accompt of the preſent Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, Studies, and Labours of the Ingenious in many conſiderable parts of the World, for <hi>Anno</hi> 1665. 1666. 1667. 1668.</p>
            <p>Obſervations on <hi>Monſieur de Sorbier</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Sprat.</hi> In <hi>duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay towards a Real Character, and a Philoſophical Language; by <hi>John Wilkins</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Ripon,</hi> and Fellow of the Royal Society. In <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Abrahami Couleij <hi>Angli Poemata Latina in quibus continenter ſex libri Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, viz. duo Herbarum, duo Florum, duo Sylvarum, &amp; unus Miſcellaneo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phyſical Reflections upon a Letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Monſieur Denis,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a new way of curing ſundry diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes by transfuſion of blood. In <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands</hi> Wants, or ſeveral Propoſals probably Beneficial for <hi>England.</hi> In <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euclidis Elementa Geometrica Novo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ac Methodo fere demonſtrata.</hi> In <hi>duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Experimental Philoſophy in 3 Books, with Obſervations about Cole-mines, by Dr. <hi>Henry Power.</hi> In <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cerebri Anatome cui acceſsit Nervorum deſcriptio &amp; uſus, Studio Dr.</hi> Tho. Willis. In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diatribae duae Medico-philoſophicae, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prior agit de fermentatione ſive de Motu inteſtino particularum in quovis corpore. Altera de Febribus, hic ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit diſſertatio Epiſtolica de urinis.
<pb facs="tcp:61559:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> Studio Dr.</hi> Tho. Willis. In <hi>duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Micrographia,</hi> or ſome Phyſiological Deſcriptions of Minute bodies, made by Magnifying-glaſſes, with Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and Inquiries thereupon; by <hi>R. Hook</hi> Fellow of the Royal Society. In <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sermons of Biſhop <hi>Brownrig.</hi> In 2 Voll. <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vetus Teſtamentum Graecum ex verſione Septuaginta Interpretum juxta Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aticanum Romae Editum.</hi> In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Graecae Linguae Hiſtoria, ſive oratio de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem linguae origine, progreſſis, atque incremento, a</hi> Gulielmo Burton Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donenſi. In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lexicon Manuale Graeco-Latinum, &amp; Latino-Graecum.</hi> Auth. Cornel. Schre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velio. In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enter into thy Cloſet, or a Method and Order for private devotion, together with particular perſwaſives thereunto and helps therein, with an Appendix concerning the frequent and holy uſe of the Lords Supper. In <hi>duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Natural and Political Obſervations made upon the Bills of Mortality, with reference to the Government, Religion, Trade, Growth, Air, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and the ſeveral Changes of the ſaid City; by Capt. <hi>John Graunt</hi> Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the Royal Society. In <hi>octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kalendarium Hortenſe,</hi> or the Gardiners Almanack, directing what he is to do Monthly throughout the year, and what Fruits and Flowers are in prime: By <hi>John Evelyn</hi> Eſquire, Fellow of the Royal Society. In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Summary of Devotions, compiled and uſed by Dr. <hi>Will. Laud,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſiderator conſidered, or a brief view of certain Conſiderations upon the <hi>Biblia Polyglotta,</hi> the <hi>Prolegome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and Appendix thereof by <hi>Br. Walton,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> In <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Claudius Mauger</hi>'s French Grammar, enriched with an exact Pronunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:61559:77"/> and many new Dialogues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an account of <hi>Englands</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, with the State of <hi>France,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, Civil, and Military, with Inſtructions for Travellers into <hi>France,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where alſo you may have choice of new Latin and French Books.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61559:77"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
